<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The apologie, or defence of a verity heretofore published concerning a medicine called aurum potabile that is, the pure substance of gold, prepared, and made potable and medicinable without corrosiues, helpfully giuen for the health of man in most diseases, but especially auaileable for the strenghning [sic] and comforting of the heart and vitall spirits the perfomers of health: as an vniversall medicine. Together with the plaine, and true reasons ... confirming the vniversalitie thereof. And lastly, the manner and order of administration or vse of this medicine in sundrie infirmities. By Francis Anthonie of London, doctor in physicke.</title>
            <author>Anthony, Francis, 1550-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 650:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The apologie, or defence of a verity heretofore published concerning a medicine called aurum potabile that is, the pure substance of gold, prepared, and made potable and medicinable without corrosiues, helpfully giuen for the health of man in most diseases, but especially auaileable for the strenghning [sic] and comforting of the heart and vitall spirits the perfomers of health: as an vniversall medicine. Together with the plaine, and true reasons ... confirming the vniversalitie thereof. And lastly, the manner and order of administration or vse of this medicine in sundrie infirmities. By Francis Anthonie of London, doctor in physicke.</title>
                  <author>Anthony, Francis, 1550-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title probably refers to his "Medicinae chymicae, et veri potabilis auri assertio", 1610.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gold --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:280:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE APOLOGIE, OR DEFENCE OF A VERITY HERETOFORE PVBLISHED CONCERNING A MEDICINE CALLED AVRVM POTABILE, that is, the pure ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Gold, prepared, and made Potable and Medicinable without corroſiues, helpefully giuen for the health of Man in moſt Diſeaſes, but eſpecially auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the ſtrenghning and comforting of the Heart and vitall Spirits the performers of health: AS AN VNIVERSALL MEDICINE. <hi>Together with the plaine, and true</hi> Reaſons, manifold and irrefragable Teſtimonies of fact, confirming the Vniuerſalitie thereof. And laſtly, the manner and order of adminiſtration or vſe of this Medicine in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie Infirmities. <hi>BY</hi> FRANCIS ANTHONIE of London, Doctor in Phyſicke.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt,</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:280:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:280:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE INDIFFERENT and Iudicious Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander the Great, King of Macedon, amongſt all other bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons of his honour, hath this not the leaſt: That in hearing of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both his eares were open to both parties, Plaintiffe, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant: That being rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, his deciſion of the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie might be vpright, not partiall. As this is the duty of euery learned and iudiciall Reader: ſo in this queſtion of mine, I cannot entertaine other thought, then expectance of all inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity: Not onely to haue eares, and all other ſenſes auerſed from the tongues and quills of idly-learned ſlanderers, but alſo reſerued vnto a generous equanimitie towards the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie and equable reply of the Defendant. Not doubting therefore (gentle Reader) of this your diſpoſition, I haue written, and dedicated to your hands and hearts, to take, reade, digeſt and cheriſh this Apologie of my Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and adminiſtration of my Eſſence and Liquor of Gold, commonly called Aurum Potabile or Potable Golde: with aſſurance of cenſure on my ſide, though diſtaſting the
<pb facs="tcp:280:3"/> A-B-C-darie and Comicall Rayler. If therefore my malicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners haue heretofore ſeduced you into ſiniſter conſtructions of this cauſe, it was not your fault, but their poſting malice, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating and foreſtalling that better and true Information, which this Apologie freely now offereth, and earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth to be ſo accepted. Many good men haue iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained againſt the Paſquelling libertie of traducing ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. If a ſufficient concluſion ſhould reſt therein, yea, or a moouing Inducement: then you with me muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that no vertue ſhall haue his due regard, no man of whatſoeuer deſert, ſhall be ſecure of his good name. My con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and ſatisfaction preſeruatiue: my ſhield and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the tainted darts of ſuch aduerſaries, ſhall bee ſecuritie againſt foule challenge, Impoſſibilitie of attaint, the warrant of truth: which in her naked ſimplicitie ſhall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine me, in the vprightneſſe of a good conſcience againſt all their attempts, and by Gods grace, powerfully deliuer me. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you therefore (indifferent and ſincere Readers) I conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate the protection both of this Treatiſe, and of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine it ſelfe therein handled. Becauſe, as no man is created ſolely for his owne particular, but for the profit and good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; (for nature hath made, and charitie commanded a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinitie and neighbourhood betwixt all men) ſo this being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially a kinde of vniuerſall Medicine: it ought not to be reſtrained from the publike te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der of profit to all men. Socrates being demanded what Countriman he was, anſwered, not only an Athenian but a Coſmopolitane, a Cittizen of that great Commonwealth, the whole world. So ought euery good Phyſition in the publike profeſſion of his facultie, not to burie his talent in the ſoyle of one Countrey, but to remember, that the very Character of his calling doth challenge the fruits of his function for all the world, ſo far as poſſible capacitie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth; ſpecially of this neereſt communitie in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
<pb facs="tcp:280:3"/> Let it not therefore ſeeme ſtrange vnto you, (worthy Readers) that without exception of Countrey or nation, I doe indefinitely appeale vnto all, and in ſuch generality conſigne theſe fruitions, which long ſtudy, labor &amp; chargeable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence haue confirmed vnto me, in my profeſſion and Practiſe of Phyſicke. Ariſt. ſaith morally (but the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is diuine) <hi>Bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munius, eò melius.</hi> The more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good thing is, the better it is. Of which followeth one reaſon of this my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent act: <hi>Omne Donu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo melius, eò comunicabilius.</hi> The better any gift is, the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municable alſo ought it to be. And as it is ſo in nature it ſelf, ſo ought it to be in the diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the poſſeſſour. I do not herein ſo propoſe, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie mine own endeuours, &amp; the perfection of this Medicine by my ſelfe made, with a ſolitarie conceit, and ambitious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, as though no perſon elſe where were ſeized of the like (and peraduenture in a higher degree of exaltation) but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging Gods bleſſings and gifts, to my ſelfe amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, I may not hide my talent in the earth: But beſide the preſent vſes hereof in moſt vrgent cauſes of health, do alſo wiſh the prouoking, and virtuous emulation in others, to incite their induſtries in the ſearch and labour of excellent neceſſity for a common good. Alſo that ſo generall a Medicine may as generally be knowne to be had, to the intent to be vſed in all places. The opinion of euery excellent, both ancient, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Phyſitions, concerning the virtue, power, efficacie and vſe of Potable gold, is conueſted in their owne writings: who do hold firme, that no Phyſition can well ſaue the performing honour of his profeſſion, without Potable gold, howſoeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he be furniſhed with herball Medicines. In which kind alſo, God hath ſtored ſo many particular adiuments, for the reliefe of mans miſerable maladies, that none ought to neglect the indagation of their virtues, the preparation of their parts, and adminiſtration of their Remedies. Which as</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:280:4"/>
            <p>I gladly and happily vſe in fit time and place, ſo I alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the like vſe to others, euen with this Potable Gold, as is commonly vſed in ſundry other Polychreſticke, or Panchre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke Medicines: according to euery preſent requiſition of occaſions and circumſtances, by the aduice of any rationall and experienced Phyſition. With which profeſſion I offer and ſubmit the reſpect and acceptance of my Inuentions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring you all, with like regard and fauour, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and embrace this my will and deſire of doing good, and to be profitable to many.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:280:4"/>
            <head>THE DIVISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF THIS TREATISE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout fiue yeares paſt I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a ſhort diſcourſe for the Aſſertion of Chymicall Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and of true Potable gold, containing theſe heades or Chapters. 1. Whether gold may be ſo diſſolued, that it become truly potable. 2. That the higheſt and moſt powerfull excellencie of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines is in Mettals. 3. That amongſt all Mettals gold hath the prerogatiue, concerning the Phyſicall vſe of Medicine. 4. Of what manner is the Art, and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to diſſolue gold, and diſtill it vp: which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is called, Drawing ouer the helme. 5. That it were requiſite by publike queſtion to examine and try this truth of this Magiſterie, that ſo the mouth of all gainſayers might be ſtopped. 6. That Potable gold deſerueth the name of a Generall or vniuerſall Medicine: and of the manifold vſe, and efficacie of mine owne Potable gold.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe of mine, containing a ſimple, naked and plaine deliuerie of a ſimple and naked truth, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:280:5"/> therefore as ſimply and plainly in words and ſtyle ſet forth, though it really ſatisfied both here and in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine parts many learned men, Iudiciall louers of truth, yet it wanted not the common lot of all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, to finde maleuolent eyes and detracting encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berers: ſuch as may ſeeme either with blinde zeale, or ignorant opinion of omniſcience, rather to repine at a fee loſt, then deſire the true knowledge of that, which they neuer intending to labour for, yet ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly deſire an imputation of criticall knowledge therein. The ſand of this deſcent was chiefely, if not only in London. The Iſſue, none haue greater cauſe to mourne for, then the Printers for want of vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or rather they which bare the charge of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: for vnto Iudiciall Readers, thoſe labours of theirs, though they were tedious and nauſeous, yet ſome recreation followed in laughing at ſo much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtetrication of ſuch mountaines in the parturition of ſuch ridiculous mice. I hope none will expect a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit anſwer of me to their moſt powerfull arguments, being, in the moſt modeſt terme, a ſhamble of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and effrenat ſcolding: but rather truth and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt falſhood &amp; words, leauing their tongs and gooſe-quils, to the iudgement and cenſure of their owne reformed and better aduiſed hearts: of which my charitie perſwades me not wholly to deſpaire: knowing ſome learned gentlemen of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, not the ſame minde, ready to bluſh at ſuch a publication, which all the learned men of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom do laugh: And who can fancy ſuch barking Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricke, wherein not only good words, are made the meaſures of madnes, but precious houres are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in frothy rablings? If they be ſtill of the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, I wiſh them thereof full contentment therein:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:280:5"/> And that therefore they would in ſome hollow crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy place ſtretch out their own ſtraines, that 1000. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of intereſt might bountifully returne them their delightfull termes and Syllogiſmes in this their new Barbara. But this my Apologie ſhall with much tranquillity, I hope, anſwer them, defend mine owne reputation and integritie, vindicate this verity que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned; giue eſtimation to potable gold, and make the vſe thereof more common. According to which intentions I haue diuided this Treatiſe in three parts. In the firſt ſhall be proued and maintained that which in my firſt printed booke was deliuered concerning gold, that it may be made potable and medicinable, and be eſteemed for a kinde of generall Medicine, or neere thereto. In the ſecond I will ſatiſfie and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prooue by irrefragable teſtimonies, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that this my Medicine ſo much canuaſed, both is made and doth conſiſt of gold, and alſo performeth the true effects, mentioned to be incident vnto pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gold. In the third part I will ſhew and teach the way how to vſe this Medicine in euery particular diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. That all pacified and indifferent perſons, fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of truth, and embracers of Gods bleſſings, may enioy the fruition thereof. Some circumſtances alſo I haue hereunto annexed, ſuch as are pertinent to this our intent.</p>
            <p>It is a controuerſed queſtion: Whether there bee or may bee made a generall or vniuerſall Medicine, good for all Diſeaſes. Many hold the negatiue. If they ſpeake preciſely of all Diſeaſes without diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſay as they doe, and conſent. For there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fatall, mortall and Incurable Diſeaſes, againſt which all conſultation and counſell of Phyſicke is bootleſſe. Therefore that my aſſertion of a generall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:280:6"/> Medicine be rightly vnderſtood, I deſire my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to bee truly and diſtinctly taken. For I know that ſome diſeaſes be natiue and hereditarie: ſome cauſed by ſome outward and ſuperuenient chance or accident: ſome proceeding of ſimple diſtemper: ſome of humors ioyned therewith. Thoſe which are natiue and hereditarie, are generally thought, and for the moſt part be all incurable, though they may in ſome kinde receiue alleuiation and eaſe: And ſome of them alſo in the title of thoſe which happen by ſuperueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent accident: As luxations, lameneſſe, Impotencies, want or ſuperfluitie of ſome ioynt, blindneſſe, deafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Ambiguitie of ſexe, &amp;c. And theſe ſo farre as they be reſtaurable and capable of Cure, are chiefely vnder that part of this facultie which is called Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and requireth the hand, though not alwaies and in all caſes. But thoſe Infirmities and Diſeaſes of the other kinde, proceeding of inward cauſes within the body, ſuch as, for the moſt part, be all Maladies whereupon all Rationall Phyſitions are exerciſed, if by adminiſtration of one Medicine they all (I meane, ſo long as they are accounted curable by Rationall Phyſitions) may be eaſed, mitigated and perhaps per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured, ſurely ſuch Medicine, ought and may be accounted reſpectiuely a generall Medicine. For as that Phyſition is to be accounted perfect, and a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Maſter of his Art which knoweth according to his title, facultie and profeſſion, how to cure all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, though he leaue and giue ouer ſome as incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; not for wnat of fit meanes and skill in all caſes of poſſibilitie, but through ineptitude and indiſpoſition of the ſubiect being vncapable of redintegration: So alſo that ſhall be accounted a Medicine vniuerſall, which cureth moſt and the greateſt diſeaſes, though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:280:6"/> not all: not through defect of efficacie in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine it ſelfe, but reſpectiuely for the inhabilitie of the ſubiect.</p>
            <p>This alſo may be proued by reaſon deriued from<note place="margin">1 The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> thoſe Medicines of Rationall Phyſitians, which for the multiplicitie of their operatiue extent to many intentions, and curing of many diſeaſes, are called Polychreſta, that is, of many vſes. For if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſuch as be helpful not to one only ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affection, but to many different diſeaſes, why is it not likewiſe conſequent and reaſonable that by help of Art, a Medicine may be made much more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſiue of efficacie vpon diſeaſes? And as it may bee made to exceede in one degree, ſo in 2. 3. 4. 100. and from Polychreſton, of many vſes, be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon, vniuerſall, of all vſes. The reaſon is all one to reaſonable men.</p>
            <p>If obiection be made, that ſuch Polychreſt is arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially made by compoſition of many things, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are diuerſitie of natures. And this vniuerſall of one onely, which implieth an impoſſibilitie of different and contrary operatiue faculties: to this I anſwere, that Polychreſts are made out of Simples without commixtion: As from Rheubarbe, Vineger, Lead, Niter, Vitriall, Opium, Camphire, and many other, wherof ſome doe both looſe and knit, ſome do heate and coole, ſome haue other contrary effects, which appeare in their operations, and are teſtified by Writers. Theſe things being thus in impure mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and vnperfect bodies, what doubt can there be made of the high prerogatiue and ſupreme excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Gold, which all the learned and experienced antiquity, and the continued deriuation from thence vnto this day haue acknowledged and magnified for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:280:7"/> the chiefe, if not only Treaſurie, and rich Cabinet of vniuerſalitie and Panchreſticke Medicine: In which all the dowers of all other Medicines, whatſoeuer are written and experimentally found, be vnited and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally incloſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas the originall of moſt diſeaſes<note place="margin">2 The ſecond reaſon.</note> ſpringeth from that, which the Phyſitions call <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperies,</hi> that is, a diſtemperature, being eſpecially in the firſt qualities, hot, cold, moiſt or drie; there is no reaſon to the contrary, but that one Medicine, being without exceſſe or defect, in equall harmonie of all qualities moſt temperate, and alſo powerfull in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, may bee ſufficient for the collection, qualify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and rectifying of all and euery ſuch diſtemper. Such a like body is gold: which notwithſtanding it be compounded of the foure Elements, yet is this in prerogatiue aboue all other naturall bodies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with an exact temperament and equalitie of the compounding Elements, and Elementall qualities. Euery one to the other three, and all foure to and among themſelues by exact naturall equalitie and perfect mixture, are ſo compounded to the perfection of this body, that it conſtantly perſiſteth in the fire without diminution. From this proportionall mixture of Elements reſulteth a temperament of ſupreme mediocritie: whereupon that our learned and famous countryman <hi>Roger Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> calleth <hi>Gold the meane betweene the foure firſt qualities.</hi> Seeing therefore by Gods gift in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it conſiſteth of ſo true an adequation and ſubtile temperament, this muſt needs appeare and ſhew it ſelfe operatiuely in conſequent effects vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe firſt qualities, and be powerfull againſt all diſtemperatures, whether hot or cold, moyſt or dry, or any their combinations: Firſt allaying and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:280:7"/> any exceſſe therein, and ſo by degrees and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion ouercomming the whole diſcord, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mediocritie of temperament betweene all. So that the generall Axiome or Rule of great <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> is here magnified: That Diſeaſes are cured by Medicines contrarie to themſelues. For the meane betwixt two extremes is no leſſe contrarie to both and either of them, then one extreme to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and more powerfull in reduction, by how much it is more habituall and fixed in the vnſpotted me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocritie and equalitie. Let this be vnderſtood of gold diſſolued and made potable, otherwiſe it is not operatiue vpon thoſe diſtempered qualities in one kinde or other</p>
            <p>The third Reaſon concerneth the temper of the bodie to bee cured. Death (ſaith <hi>Galen</hi>) doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies<note place="margin">3 The third reaſon.</note> follow the vnmeaſurable or exceſſiue diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratures of the Heart. So likewiſe doe Diſeaſes. For all parts of the bodie languiſh with the Heart. Let vs therefore conſider a little the Emperie of the Heart in mans bodie, how by his owne heate and vitall ſpirit, it raigneth ouer, and in all parts of the bodie. Let vs alſo take into conſideration the diſtemperature of other parts making impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon the Heart, and ſo are cauſes of languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and death. VVhich beeing on either ſide certaine, then it muſt alſo bee true, that if golde adminiſtred doe reſtore integritie of temperament to the Heart, the other parts and members of the bodie ſhall alſo receiue comfort, ſtrength, reſtauration, and finally life to the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. VVherefore the firſt office of euerie good Phyſition is, to haue ſpeciall regarde, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:280:8"/> and vphold the ſpirituall functions of his diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed patient, which all haue their originall from the heart. For if he ſuffer them to quaile, and ouer much to bee deiected, all Cordialls will then come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably. That admonition is iuſt and neceſſarie <hi>Firſt ſtrengthen and comfort the Heart, then apply for the Diſeaſe,</hi> if neede be: for oft times, the Heart being well corroborated, the Diſeaſe imminent vaniſheth. But ſome will aske, how gold, ſo hard, ſolide and compact, and therefore indigeſtable by any ſtrength of mans ſtomacke, can paſſe from thence to the heart, and ſtrengthen, comfort, rectifie and reſtore it; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſidering that theſe and ſuch like faculties come to it by the plentie of pure, cleere, and ſubtill ſpirits of the blood, which cannot be made of any thing not digeſted both in the Stomack and Lyuer, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not of gold. In anſwer whereof I ſay, that long and daily obſeruation hath confirmed, that many things naturally are effected by the hidden and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall properties of ſome things, whereof no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of man can giue a certaine and vndiſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manifeſt cauſe or reaſon. We ſee the affinitie of natures betweene Iron and the Lode-ſtone, and the pointing of this to the North Pole. Of which kinde there be infinite exemplarie inſtances. Neither doe the moſt learned Phyſitions and beſt Philoſophers ſo well agree vpon the reaſons of thoſe Purging Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines which they call Electiue, as appropriate ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to one humour: and diuers others to ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part of the bodie, yea and to ſome ſpeciall diſeaſes: but that a great part of them doe flie to theſe hidden and ſpecificall properties, ſome in the ſame, ſome in other termes. In which ranke if wee marſhall gold, what Lieuetenant will chide? He certainly muſt be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:280:8"/> ſome ouerweening man, that will queſtion theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues of gold, that hath read ſo many notable and famous Authors for that affirmatiue aſſertion, part whereof I haue cited in my other booke, being but one Rank of a whole Armie. Here I will only trouble the Reader with a few lines out of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Phyſition and excellent Philoſopher <hi>Arnald. Gold altereth the euill condition of mans body, clenſeth and reneweth it. The vertue of many things may come neere the particulars of the operation hereof, but no one performe it all. But potable gold alone is it which worketh theſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous effects: this is not ſubiect to corruption, but is agreeable to the Complexion and temperament of man. It doth neither heate, nor coole, nor moyſten, nor dry: but is temperate in all temperature, and exceedeth all things in durabilitie: It hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth a cold ſtomacke, and giueth courage to Cowards and fearefull hearts: It helpeth the paſſions of the Heart: It is good againſt Melancholy: It comforteth naturall heate and tempereth the ſame, neither may any thing be compared to it or ſupply the ſtead thereof. The vertue thereof is manifeſt in the ſubſtance of it. It clenſeth and clarifieth by reaſon of the naturall heate it hath. It giueth high and ſupreame tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aboue all other things, by reaſon of the great tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it ſelfe: and beeing it ſelfe moſt durable, it cauſeth continuance and durabilitie, according to naturall poſſibility in other things, and preſerueth mans body. And becauſe it is like to the Complexion of mens bodie, therefore if it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as it ought, it will ioyne and incorporate thereunto. But all the ſecret is in the preparation of it, which the wiſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers haue concealed. It confirmeth and keepeth ſound the ſubſtance of the Heart, and preſerueth it, and clarifieth the ſubſtance of the ſpirits, and ſendeth good blood to the skin, and with a light and eaſie abſterſion preſerueth beauty as in youth.</hi> Thus he writeth, as alſo in other places of this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:280:9"/> Author you may reade many admirable effects and vertues of gold both ſolide and potable. How gold is ſo powerfull a Cordiall and ſo generall a Medicine, is held a very difficult queſtion to finde the cauſe and reaſon thereof. Let euery mans opinion bee free to himſelfe. I will without preiudice to any other briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew you my opinion. I take it for granted that gold of all mixed bodies is moſt equall and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in the Elements and elementall qualities, ſo that moyſture with heat as agent, drineſſe with coldnes as patient and ſubiect to action, are inſeparably with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall concordance perfectly ioyned. Wherefore gold is reſpectiuely a body not only incorruptible in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, fire, ayre, and earth, and as it were an earthly i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of eternitie, but alſo moſt conuenient, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and as it were allied to and with the heart of man, which of his hot moyſture doth worke the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſpirits, and maintaine the arteriall beatings of the pulſe in all parts of the bodie. And this tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of gold muſt bee conſidered two waies. Firſt (as Scholers call it) Arithmetically: hence commeth the equalitie and equabilitie of qualities elementarie in the compact and ſolide body thereof, not reſolued into the permanent forme of potable liquor. In this conſideration it were very hard for learned Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that build ſo much vpon and preſſe authoritie, to deny that gold hath and actiuely doth ſhew many great effectiue vertues, ſeeing the Catalogue is ſo great of many notable and famous Phyſitions which extoll the effects thereof, and at this day doe vſe it ſo much; as of gold quenched in wine, boyled in broth, giuen in limell or foyle in Conſerues and Electuaries. The hope and end thereof in all their intentions, is to Corroborate and comfort the heart. And this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:280:9"/> temperature in and of gold is habituate and coeſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall with the whole ſubſtance, matter and forme, in all the Elements both actiue and paſſiue. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not the materiall but the formal Eſſence is moſt operatiue and profeſſor of the noble Elements, fire and ayre, from whence reſulteth in an indiſſoluble bond, heate and moyſture ſo friendly agreeable to mans nature. Therefore gold in his naturall coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſoliditie, cannot ſo fully according to the inward power of his naturall efficacie and vertue, ſhew and performe the effects thereof, as being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, opened, and made potable, that the Elements and elementall qualities may more freely both worke and be wrought vpon, and be brought from their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiality to actiuitie in application to the body of man. For then the agent and formall vertues, fire and ayre be predominant in their exaltation. Whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, being communicated &amp; applied to &amp; with the ſpirits of our body, is to refreſh, comfort &amp; ſtrengthen the heart: renew, reſtore, and increaſe the ſpirits, by that wonderfull facultie, and neere equalitie as it were brotherhood which it hath to them. And this in the ſecond conſideration of the temperament of Gold Geometricall in that different reſpect, as the other is called Arithmeticall. In which that propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate qualitie friendly and concordant to the heart and temperament of man, and that complexio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moyſt heate or hot moyſture, is preualent or predominant. And one chiefe reaſon why <hi>Arnald</hi> before cited and very many others of vnreprooue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able authoritie, doe ſo much commend, and with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſecrecie admire the excellent dowers of gold, is, that being made potable, it reſtoreth, augmenteth and preſerueth that our <hi>humidum radicale,</hi> and <hi>calidum
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:280:10"/> innatum,</hi> Naturall heate and moyſture, (vnderſtand them complexioned not diſtinct) and ſo with reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue poſſibilitie, prolongeth life, and keepeth backe old age, I meane the ſenſe of the defects and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof.</p>
            <p>If it be obiected that this exact temperature and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note> of mixture in gold being ſuppoſed, it cannot actiuely operate or worke any thing in mans bodie, becauſe, as euery action commeth from or by meanes of ſome predominant qualitie, ſo equalitie without diſparagement keepes all in an vndefeazeable bond of an irreſoluble compound. I anſwer thus. In caſes where the intemperature or diſtemper of the diſeaſe (or the degree thereof in ſome caſes) is not yet knowne, the doctrine poſitiue and counſell of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is, to vſe and adminiſter temperate Medicines, which ſhall not be offenſiue manifeſtly to any quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but indifferent and allowable to all. If this be done with good aduiſe and reaſon: in ſuch like caſe, it muſt needs be far more conſonant to reaſon, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull to the patient, to giue ſuch a Medicine as is not only temperate by qualification, but ſo preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely excellent therein, that it cannot loſe that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature and the conſequent efficacie thereof, by the force of any thing conſonant or diſſonant. Which is farre otherwiſe in all vegetables reputed equall in temperament, becauſe they are apt in ſome caſes to cauſe dangerous diſtemperature in mans body. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are plentifull. But for inſtance take Manna it ſelfe reputed a very temperate laxatiue, yet very eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſelfe turning into a hot Cholerick humour, and encreaſing the ſame, and the diſtemperatures and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes conſequent thereupon according to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and inclination of the body receiuing it. Of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:280:10"/> which there is no feare in the vſe of gold, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aforeſaid. Therefore whether the Tenure be: That Contraries be cured by Contraries, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the diſeaſe and the cauſe thereof, the qualitie of the Medicine is remedy: Or that like are conſerued by their like, with regard to the ſtrength of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and comfort of the heart, according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Hippocrates:</hi> Gold (as hath beene prooued) muſt needs be in both intentions the fitteſt and moſt conuenient Medicine and remedy for diſeaſes of what temper or diſtemper ſoeuer, being aduiſedly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: ſpecially being Philoſophically opened, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and made potable:</p>
            <p>That there may bee a generall or vniuerſall Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine<note place="margin">4 The fourth reaſon.</note> is alſo prooued, by conſideration taken from the nature of the perſon diſeaſed, with reference to the diſeaſe. For if the diſeaſe be ſtrong, like a heauie burden preſſing the patient, and the poore patient weake not able to beare out the Critical day of happy iudgement of iſſue of the maladie; I aske in this caſe what ought to be done. Certainly, rather enable the body to the end of the Combate, by comforting and ſtrengthning the heart, then vainly attempt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue the log, and ſuffer him to ſinke vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. For, not the Medicine, but nature alone is the true phyſition, curing all infirmities, if ſhe be not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, or that ſhe be ſo releeued, that ſtrength in her be maintained. It is not vnlike by compariſon vnto the charge of ſumpter Mules or Pack-horſes, which oft times vſe to bee fed trauelling that they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to carry their burdens to the Inne, not diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vntimely of their packes. And by this meanes they neede not be vnloaden at euery bayte; but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendred vnder their loads for the quicker diſpatch.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:280:11"/> So no diſeaſe is cured, the ſtrength not maintained: but contrarily by perfect Methode the ſtrength and power of the body is by degrees to bee reſtored and comforted, that the diſeaſe may be both reſolued, and life maintained. To this purpoſe did <hi>Arnaldus</hi> write in theſe words. <hi>The only intention of ancient Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions was, to giue vigor and ſtrength vnto nature: Who being ſtrengthned, performeth whatſoeuer is expedient. And by this meanes they neuer did ouerthrow any man. Therefore neuer ceaſe to worke with Cordialls in adminiſtration of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</hi> This is the counſell of <hi>Arnald.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, many diſeaſes proceed from obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">The fift rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> of ſome viſcous, ſlymie and mucilaginous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not ſeparated in the veſſels of concoction, by their imbecillity, either naturall, or accidentall. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if this obſtruent matter be ſubtiliated, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhall thereby be taken away, &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both the diſeaſe and accidents of the diſeaſe cured. Of ſuch kinds of Obſtructions, beſides other diſeaſes, many kinds of fevers doe ariſe, burning, rotten, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick, peſtilent, &amp;c. Alſo many and dangerous ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes both hot and cold. Againſt which though Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine made of vegetables doe often very much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile: yet becauſe for the moſt part they be too weak, and leaue no ſolide and laſting impreſſion: or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe worke ſo violently, and ſeldome without ſome offence, ſcarce euer with ſuch temper, gentlenes and ſincerity as is requiſite. Therefore that Medicine which being moſt temperate and equally graduated to the Elementall harmonie of mans body, ought iuſtly to be preferred both before them and all of that kind. For ſuch one cannot by his coldneſſe offend the complexioned parts, nor by his heate the hot: but by opening and ſo promotiuely taking away the Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, be equally &amp; certainly profitable to all. <hi>Galen</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:280:11"/> teacheth that the cauſe is to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, by finding out, and applying the true contrary of euery alterable nature. As to cure any diſeaſe coming of and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on Obſtruction, is the diſſoluing of matter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruent, &amp; opening the Obſtruction. This counſell we ought to follow in al ſuch caſes, in opening that which is forcibly ſhut. And then gentle and quiet reſtitution commeth of temperament to all diſtempered parts. For, whether the exceſſe were in heate or cold, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits which were ſhut vp in priſon, now ſet at liberty, are refreſhed, recouer their former vigor, and health to the whole body. If the blood (ſaith <hi>Hippocrat.</hi>) be ſtopped in his courſe, and the ſpirit with it, it cauſeth chylneſſe, numneſſe, giddines, loſſe or hinderance of ſpeach, heauines &amp; paine of the head &amp; convulſions, after which follow many kinds of the falling ſicknes which be accounted cold diſeaſes. In briefe, it is moſt euident, that only Obſtructions be the cauſe of many and ſundry diſeaſes, not only different, but directly contrary each to other. Therfore as one cauſe brought them in, ſo may one Medicine expell them.</p>
            <p>But pauſe a while. It may be demanded how hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection.</note> ſo exorbita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; abounding as they do in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of many men, ſhal be emptied from thence by the force of any medicine, whoſe faculty is not to expel or purge by the common paſſage, and whoſe intent is to be only ſtrengthning and comforting the heart.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer: It is true, that in many diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes<note place="margin" type="runSum">Solution.</note> the abundance of humors are ſuch cauſes, that except they be purged away in due and conuenient time and order, it is ſcarſe poſſible to hope for a ſound recouerie: in vvhich caſe if ſome gentle Purgation, together vvith the adminiſtration of this vniuerſall Medicine be vſed, both the ſtrength ſhall be better maintained, ſooner recouered, and the diſeaſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:280:12"/> Yet though no purgation be giuen, but onely this vniuerſall Medicine at times adminiſtred, ſuch is the vertue thereof, that Nature it ſelfe being ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and comforted aboue the malice of the offending humors and the diſeaſe, will expell the burden of thoſe humors by the moſt conuenient paſſages which that caſe may require, whether it be by ſiege, vomit, vrine, ſweate, or other exitures. For the Phyſition at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, is not directer and Maſter, but miniſter and ſeruant in fit adminiſtration vnto nature: which being comforted and ſtrengthned, will helpe her ſelfe beyond all hope and conceit of man, as hath bin of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten found to the admiration of the greateſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors which hitherto haue written, and happeneth daily in our owne experience. In all diſeaſes the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions part is, to promote the indeauour of nature to expel the offending humors by thoſe paſſages, which herſelfe ſheweth and directeth; with diſcretion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene criticall and ſymptomaticall euacuations, and of the conueniencie of a few circumſtances follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the particularities of the diſeaſe: Of this I could eaſily and plentifully bring many irrefragable and demonſtratiue reaſons: but they may partly bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by that which is already ſaid, and partly are written by diuers others graue and learned Authors. Therfore I wil follow breuitie, &amp; only ſet down a few lines out of that profound and ſingular Philoſopher <hi>Raymund Lully:</hi> who in the 32. Chapter of the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his Teſtament writeth thus. <hi>Bleſſed be our glorious and omnipotent God who hath giuen mankinde knowledge and vnderſtanding to ioyne and integrate the confuſed parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularitie of all Medicines with one reall vniuerſalitie, by which all things be and continue rectified. Therefore Sonne I warne thee, if thou deſireſt to be a perfect Phyſition, ſet not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:280:12"/> thy Practiſe on the particularities of Medicine, or the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intentions of Phyſicke, becauſe they be confuſed, and at this day not ſound, nor perfect. For nature cannot endure them, by reaſon of their too much confuſion, but is beſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ſatisfied with and in one only Medicine. Becauſe there is but one Medicine truly curing all Infirmities, and comforting the ſpirituall vertues and powers of life, &amp;c.</hi> And a litttle after in the ſame. <hi>He that knoweth how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce moſt particularities or vertues (for the intention of Curing diſeaſes) vnto one vniuerſalitie (of ſubiect) ſhall bee the moſt excellent amongſt Phyſitions. In particular Medicines vertues bee confuſed: but in an vniuerſall, they bee reall, vnited, and actiue, as the whole courſe of nature ſheweth. And this is Medicina, Medicinarum, ſuperlatiuely by excellencie and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue the Medicine of Medicines. And hee that hath ſuch a Medicine, hath a pretious gift of God. For it is an incomparable treaſure.</hi> Thus far <hi>Raymund:</hi> who though he there ſpeake of that great and high Philoſophicall ſecret, yet he plainly witneſſeth that there is in nature a vniuerſall Medicine: which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be made of gold, or gold made of it, It matte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not much, for either way it ſufficiently proueth, the excellent properties of gold moſt agreeable to mans nature; which hauing thus farre prooued, I will here end this firſt part of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus, vnto moderate and well tempered Iudgements (for my intent and purpoſe in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) prooued, that there hath bin, and therefore may be a Panchreſticall Medicine, for which very many learned are either ſearchers themſelues, or witneſſes of other mens happines in attaining the ſame: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the peruicacie of ſome is ſuch, that againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment and ſenſe it ſelfe, they will (peraduenture
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:280:13"/> conſciouſly) pretend the Impoſſibilitie &amp; maintaine the negatiue: &amp; ſome againe, though yeelding a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie &amp; maintaining the affirmatiue, wil fight in the ſhadow of one inſtance: contending, that thogh they granted it may be; yet this ſubiect of mine, this my potable gold hath not either the true, or neere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of that ſo renowned and famouſly mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Medicine, powerfull and auaileable in all diſeaſes that may happen to men: I will applie my ſelfe to their ſatisfaction. My anſwer ſhall be breefe, and of two ſorts. Firſt by Reaſon: ſecondly, by manifeſt and cleere demonſtration of effects, of manifold experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and witneſſes beyond exception: which be the maine pillers &amp; onely neceſſary ſubſtructions of all knowledg in matter controuertible amongſt men.</p>
            <p>Concerning the proofes of reaſon, I haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſatisfied that point in my other booke in the fourth, fift, and ſixt chapters. Yet further I pray conſider here with me, that there bee many pathes leading to the ſame Towne, and many waies to one and the ſame end. Some in their endeauours and purſuite for the attaining of a vniuerſall Medicine labour in Minerals and thoſe Mettals which reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely bee called, and are vnperfect: Some in Salts: ſome in vegetables, ſome in the Animall kinde: euery one dittying the ſound of the bell anſwerable to his owne tune. Let each of them therefore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Iſſue of his owne labors. I force not againſt them. But freely profeſſe that in the perſwaſion of thoſe reaſons which haue lead mee, I reſolutely ſet downe my reſt for this ſcrutinie in naturall gold, and therein haue employed my Induſtry: with what ſucceſſe and happie Iſſue, I appeale to the moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, true and vncontrollable Iudge and Doctreſſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:280:13"/> which is experience. The centonary Fropperies of Alphabetarias, of <hi>Aurum non Aurum,</hi> ſhall nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the vindicting of this conſtant truth, that by my preparation, <hi>Aurum non Aurum,</hi> gold hath beene ſo altered in and from the compacture and ſoliditie of his primitiue body; and in that reſpect it may bee called, and truly is, <hi>non Aurum,</hi> not gold, but deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, concerning the groſſe body, and altered into a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, penetrant and volatile nature, and ſo exalted into the full actiuitie of a moſt precious Medicine, with all the powerfull explications of healthfull and helpfull myſteries which nature hath ſealed in that body, and left to the induſtrious labour of man to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. For gold is the Embleme of a magnificent and moſt princely Pallace, drawing the beholders of his naturall luſter, to ſearch what excellent Iewels bee contained within that outward wall of ſo rich promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Which though they be many and admirable, yet few attaine to the fruition thereof, becauſe by externe apparences, they ayme at the latent and hidden ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: neither doe they know the right key to vnlock that rich Cabinet. And although I cannot ſufficiently declare, nor prize, all the faculties (which be reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely innumerable) of this bountifull treaſury: yet I may and doe confidently acknowledge and profeſſe, that I haue found in vſe &amp; practiſe very many of great worth; which as in themſelues, for the vſe of men they be of great worth, and eſtimation, ſo for them, man is reciprocally bound both to ackwowledg &amp; thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully embrace, as Gods large bleſſing; who comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to knock at theſe gates of Nature, that they may be opened vnto vs, that ſo we may finde and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the treaſures locked therein. What man amongſt thouſand hath found out and perfected the like
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:280:14"/> magiſteriall ſecret? Who is he among many, that hath not tyred his teeth in the hard ſhell, neuer inabled by cracking it, to come to the ſweet kernell, in which dwelleth this mellite and gentle liquor of gold? But I will leaue this digreſſion, and returne to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded end.</p>
            <p>There is no queſtion but that a Medicine made of<note place="margin">1. Reaſon.</note> naturall gold, diſſolued without things corroſiue, and brought into a ſubſtance in forme like hony, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinable, potable, and diſperſeable into any liquor, is both excellent, and iuſtly to be reputed potable gold. But this Medicine of mine, made and conſiſting in it ſelfe of gold, is ſuch (as I haue before prooued and ſhall further hereafter proue) therefore it is, and ought to be acknowledged for true potable gold. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition needeth none other proofe, then the conſent of all famous writers of and vpon potable gold: The Aſſumption, whereupon the Inference and Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion dependeth, is prooued in my firſt publiſhed booke, as alſo out of manifeſt demonſtration, not pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, to my ſelfe, but publike in the ſight of many, not onely once done, but ſundry times iterated: in which proceedings, the demonſtratiue tokens mentioned in Art, are apparent: the Inſtrumentall water which was in the forme of common water before it was put vpon the gold, in few daies becommeth tincted, with a deepe and ruddy colour, alſo when the Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall water ſo tincted, ſhall be diſtilled away, the ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of gold remaineth in forme of hony as by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers is ſpecified. In the whole magiſterie, Art or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe I haue not kept any thing ſecret, ſauing the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall water as <hi>Raymund</hi> teſtifieth. But ſome will ſay, If this be that true Potable gold, why do you make it common to others? Good Sirs, forſooth I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:280:14"/> becauſe it is ſuch, therefore I make it common, concerning the vſe: Which being profitable to all, challengeth the right and law of nature and charitie, to be communicated to al. But that other great ſecret of the Philoſopher, not communicable to others, is onely profitable to the Author himſelf. And therfore let not this be the leſſe precious in it ſelfe, becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable men receiue health and comfort thereby? The ſunne giueth viſible light to the whole world. Is it therefore an inferiour Planet vnto <hi>Mercury</hi> which ſeldome appeares in the ſight of men?</p>
            <p>Againe. That Medicine which really performeth<note place="margin">2. Reaſon.</note> the true and proper vnqueſtioned effects of <hi>Aurum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabile,</hi> being eſſentially made of the ſaid ſubiect, ought and needes muſt be accounted true potable gold. But this Medicine of mine, hath produced the notable effects, only proper to potable gold. Therfore it muſt needes be the ſame. An affirmatiue argument from the effect to the cauſe is good and ſtrong: as likewiſe from the cauſe to the effect. In the holy Scriptures, a Prophet ſhall be iudged great, by his great workes. As <hi>Elias, Eliſa,</hi> and the Apoſtles raiſed the dead, as our Sauiour Chriſt did. (It being proper only to the power of God) whoſe doctrine they as forerunners; theſe as ſucceeders preached, in one verity, and the ſame diuine gift. The Analogie and proportionall deduction of Inference, is a like true in Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and in all workes both of Nature and Art, whether ſingular or conioyned. So our Potable gold, brought from the potentialitie of natures lock, vnto the actiuitie, which artificiall opening exciteth and manifeſteth, is knowne by his owne proper and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable efficacies and effects, largely affirmed in my other booke. The Aſſumption of this Argument,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:280:15"/> drawing the concluſion, I will further heereafter, by examples confirme.</p>
            <p>The third Reaſon may be taken from the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie<note place="margin">3. Reaſon.</note> and wonderfull manner of working in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and reſolution of gold, whereby it is brought from fixation, to volatility, and ſo made potable. Therefore I ſay thus. Whoſoeuer can ſo diſſolue the body of gold, that it ſhall not by any Art be reduced againe into fixed ſolide gold, but ſo perſiſt; doubtles hath made potable gold, medicinable and profitable for the health of man. But by Gods bleſſings in my endeauours, I haue often times done this, and ſtil can doe it: therefore doubtleſſe I haue often times made, and ſtill can make potable gold, medicinable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for mans health. The dependence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of this propoſition ſtandeth in this: That gold in his primitiue, naturall, hard, compact body, cannot communicate his internall vertues in mans body; and therefore is not medicinable. For then the formalitie of gold is not looſened from the bridle, or freed from the bodily priſon, and bonds of coagulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore not eaſily worke vpon the ſubiect whereunto it is applied. But contrariwiſe, being vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matly and irreducibly ſolute, it is then apt for action. So that if the ſubſtance of gold be exalted in his exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate colour, it is a true token that it is made ſubtile, attenuate, and therefore Medicinable; and that the aery and fiery parts, or Elementalitie thereof, are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant ouer the earthy and watery. And in this manner preſeruing the naturall vnitie of the whole compound, doe draw them (not altering the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, but ſubtiliating the ſubſtance) in the exalted ſymboliſme of the ſame Elements. The Aſſumption hath the ſame proofe and confirmation which the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:280:15"/> other before: that is, my very often and almoſt dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience, whereof, if need be I, can produce ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eye-witneſſes of eminent rancke, and amongſt them ſome learned Phyſitions, againſt whom no one dare mutter an exception. But as <hi>Auicen</hi> in his booke de <hi>Animá</hi> maketh three kinds of proofe. 1. <hi>Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. 2. Logicall,</hi> and 3. <hi>Senſible</hi> by ſight: of which it is to be vnderſtood, that by Sophiſticall there he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not falſe or counterfeit cauillings. But leauing that apart, I will content my ſelfe with the other twaine. The Logicall part of which we haue hitherto diſcourſed by infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of reaſon: And now, will we proceeede to the third, being of ſenſible and eye-witneſſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:280:16"/>
            <head>EXPERIMENTS AND OCVLARE <hi>TESTIMONIES, A</hi> FEVV DRAVVEN OVT OF A <hi>GREAT NVMBER, BY WHICH</hi> the Wonderfull vertues of this my Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gold in the Curing of Diſeaſes are fully <hi>ſhewed, perhibited and auouched, by</hi> oculare and ſenſible teſtimonies, free from all future challenge and queſtion.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>A PROTESTATION OF THE Author, to the writers of theſe Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or Letters following.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onorable, Worſhipfull and Worthy perſons, I intreate your curteſies, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate humanities, not to take in ill part or make ſiniſter conſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I haue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your ſpeciall allowances &amp; warrants, publiſhed theſe your letters written vnto me, concerning the effects and ſucceſſes in the adminiſtration of my Potable
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:280:16"/> gold. Proteſting hereby, that I entertaine not the leaſt thought of wronging any of you; but beeing compulſarily enforced to the neceſſarie defence of my Integritie and good name, intentiouſly ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the oppugning of this Medicine, which is the ſubiect of this Diſcourſe. I pray you all willingly to conſent to this auerrment of your owne conſciences, and teſtifying both the Innocencie of mee, and vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full neceſſity of a Medicine prooued by your ſelues in ſo many caſes of dangers, left and forſaken after all other knowne Remedies rankly attempted: and prognoſtically reputed deſperate. Which your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, I doubt not ſhall record an honorable memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of you, in the maintenance of ſo neceſſarie, and healing truth. I ſhall neuer faile by any my habilities, to be ready in any kinde of ſeruices of good offices to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:280:17"/>
               <head>TRANSMARINE <hi>TESTIMONIES.</hi> THE VSE OF THE POTABLE GOLD BROVGHT OVT <hi>OF ENGLAND, AND PRESENTED</hi> TO HIS SACRED IMPERIALL Maieſtie I doe approoue, by the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſucceſſe in two caſes of</hi> mine experience.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, I gaue one ounce waight thereof to a yong man naturally ſtrong, but then farre ſpent with a malignant feuer, being <hi>febris inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> with Idleneſſe of his Braine. After taking thereof he ſlept, and in his ſleepe, auoided through his mouth, foure long and round wormes, liuing and quicke. So was he quit and free both from the feuer, congelation, and diſtemper of the Braine. Notwithſtanding many Remedies had beene before prooued vpon him, and he had lyen in this caſe foure weekes extremely ſicke, in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:280:17"/>
                  <p>AN other alſo recouered by this potable gold; Who beeing poſſeſſed of a Quartane feuer, (which tooke him in the Autumne or fall of the leafe, and held him all winter) and was thereby ſo weakened, that his ſtrength ſeemed vtterly decayed, and ready to fall into a Dropſie. This man after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Purgations, tooke of me an ounce of this Potable gold, in the diſtilled water of <hi>Carduus Benedictus:</hi> whereby hee fell into ſo ſtrange and vnaccuſtomed ſweat, as I cannot reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber euer to haue read, or heard of the like. For beſide that it was naturall, with out o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impulſion, and ſo abundant that two perſons had their hands full in drying him, yet it ſo continued 3. daies and 3. nights. But the moſt wonderfull thing of all was, that in this extraordinary ſweat, and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from meate the time of three daies and nights, he was ſo farre from fainting, for ſo much as any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon could obſerue, that with this naturall and ſponta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall euacuation, he did euery houre waxe ſtronger, luſtier, and more cheerefull: And at the end of theſe daies, he was throughly recouered and in perfect health.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I doe witneſſe this IOHN ATHMESTETT IN Pubemheimb and Weyer, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. in Phyſicke, and Phyſition to the Sacred Imperiall Maieſtie.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:280:18"/>
               <head>Right worſhipfull Sir.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing read your true Aſſertion of that high Medicine the <hi>Aurum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabile,</hi> and heard relation made of the ſtrange and wonderfull effects of the ſame, by my <hi>Lord Roſſe</hi> his Maieſties Ambaſſadour, <hi>Sir N. Drury.</hi> and <hi>Mr. Stafford,</hi> with diuers others noble and gentlemen of England that were at this Election &amp; Coronation in <hi>Frankforth,</hi> I could &amp; would not omit to viſit you with theſe few lines, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreating you, that for my pay, I might be partaker of this ſo great a gift of God. And hauing vnderſtood by the letters of <hi>Sir Henery Cary,</hi> that 4. ounces of this high medicine are ſould for twenty ſhillings, I haue intreated this gentleman to lay out foure pounds ſterling, that I might haue 16. ounces of it. The which, if I may attaine at your hands, as alſo the doſe, the manner and time of exhibiting it (for vnwilling would I erre contrary to your experience) I ſhall euer hold my ſelfe bound and behoulding vnto you. Thus humbly beſeeching you that for common ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſake, you would not let me faile of my Intreatie, I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your though vnknowne yet euer louing friend IAMES MOSAN, Phyſition to his Highneſſe.</signed>
                  <dateline>CASSELL IN HESSEN <date>THIS 11. Iuli. 1612.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:280:18"/>
               <p>RIght Worſhipful Sir, I thank you moſt highly for your <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> which you ſent me: which indeede I do neuer vſe, but in neceſſitie, when other Medicines wil ſhew no help at al. I haue tried the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof in extreame vomitings: In the paſſion of the hart: In malicious and contagious Dyſenteries or bloody fluxes: In the riſing or ſuffocation of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the falling ſickneſſe by reaſon thereof: In the Colike. In all which diſeaſes after all other helps inward and outward haue failed, one doſe of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine did effect ſo much, that all theſe patients after they had taken it, as it were in few houres recouered their health. I haue alſo tried it, in that diſeaſe which is called <hi>Melancholia hypocondriaca</hi> (in Engliſh ſome call it the Melancholie of the gutts) but haue not found that effect as in the former. Yet it hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted the party maruellouſly.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Sleuſingen <date>24. of Febr. 1612.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your euer good friend IAMES MOSAN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:280:19"/>
               <p>VVOrſhipfull D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Anthony,</hi> you may thinke me either forgetfull, or vnthankfull for your manifold curteſies towards me. But the truth is, I can finde no conuenient meanes as I would, how to ſhew my thankfulneſſe; and therefore conſtrained to die your debter.</p>
               <p>Your <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> is an admirable Medicine in moſt Diſeaſes. I haue giuen it in the beginning of a Podagricall fit: Whereupon the patient fell into a ſweat, and therewithall his paine ceaſed, and the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent walked againe in ſhort ſpace. Alſo in the bloudy flux I haue vſed it, In the falling ſickneſſe: In the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous Menſtruall flux of women: In the wormes of yong children; In the Meaſels and ſmall Pocks: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in all the Diſeaſes of the Matrice, it is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Remedie. Let all them that haue written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, talke idely &amp; nothing to the purpoſe. This grant them, that they haue read much, and write learnedly, but nothing to diſprooue your Medicine: That little experience that I haue made of it, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue found, is ſufficient to ſhew their vanitie. So I deſire to be commended to you, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Caſſell <date>this 16. of Auguſt. 1614.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your moſt louing friend Iames Moſanus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:280:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt that I may the better ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe, declare and ſatisfie this relation by letters ſent vnto me from this ſaid wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, truly learned, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly adorned gentleman</hi> Iames Moſan <hi>Doctor of Phyſicke, and primate Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in ordinary to the Landſgraue of Heſſ. I thinke it not amiſſe here to inſert that which came from an Engliſh gentleman named</hi> Alexander Oldfield, <hi>then beeing in Germany; who in the yeare 1613. the 22. of Iuly, in certaine letters ſent to Sir</hi> Richard Norton <hi>Knight, and by him ſhewed vnto me, amongſt other matters writeth thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One thing I had almoſt forgotten, which I intreate your Worſhip to certifie to my Lord<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>, the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Wincheſter; that being at Hall the 28. of May, I met with the Landſgraue of Heſſen his Doctor of Phyſicke, which ſpeakes Engliſh very well (for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his degrees in Oxford.) And talking with him about Phyſicke, hee asked whether I knew <hi>Doctor Anthony.</hi> I told him that I had heard of him. He told me, that his <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> was excellent Phyſicke: and the firſt experience that he had made of it, was on a maide of 21. yeares of age, which was fore troubled with the falling ſickneſſe, and ſince that time ſhe was neuer troubled with it, being now aboue a yeare paſt.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:280:20"/> He gaue her one ounce therof at a time, and that ſelfe ſame day ſhe fell into the paſſions of that Diſeaſe ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times, &amp; (as I ſaid before) ſhe neuer fel ſince into them. Hee gaue it alſo to a childe not aboue foure monethes old, which was grieuouſly troubled with that diſeaſe, and it helpt the childe preſently.</p>
               <p>Alſo he gaue it to one that was troubled with the bloudy flux, and was brought ſo low with it, that no man thought he could haue recouered: he gaue him one ounce at a time, and that but once only, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly he recouerd, and is very well.</p>
               <p>He gaue it alſo to a woman which was in childe-bed, and was exceeding weake with the ſcouring, and nothing could ſtay it but that <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi> For as ſoone as ſhee tooke that, ſhee recouered. This himſelfe reporteth, and wiſheth that he dwelt neere vnto <hi>D. Anthony,</hi> that he might haue I nough there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as neede required.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ALEX. OLDFIELD.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:280:20"/>
               <p>SIr. I am perſwaded that you admire my long ſilence, which proceedes from no other then ſundrie great buſineſſes, &amp;c. I had occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend ſome of your <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> which I had for my proper vſe, to a principall gentleman here in the Emperours Court. By whoſe meanes I haue bin of late much ſent vnto by ſundrie principall perſons, ſome dangerouſly ſick, to impart it vnto them; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Baron of Creſſy, who had two ſonnes ſicke of the ſmall Poxe: the Eldeſt of about 19. and the other of 17. yeares of age. The Eldeſt died without taking any of the <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> becauſe they about him thought it was in vaine, and that they were both too farre ſpent. The other, beeing as dangerouſly ſicke, tooke it, and is thereupon recouered. The father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not being well, hath likewiſe vſed it, and doth finde himſelfe much comforted, and wel againe by it. Many more in like manner. I haue beene ſo liberall of my ſtore, that it is almoſt ſpent. Many doe wiſh I had ſuch quantitie by me that they might haue a good part of it for their money. Wherefore ſend me I pray you a good quantitie of the three ſorts, with the price therof. Send it either by ſome of our Marchants that are to come to this next Mart at Frankfurth, or elſe by ſome frind of truſt in the company of the <hi>Count Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> or the <hi>Lady Elizabeth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>VIENNA <date>THIS THIRD OF Feb. 1612. Stile Brit.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your very aſſured and louing friend S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Steph. Leſeiur Knight, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to the Emperour.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:280:21"/>
               <p>VVOrthy and learned friend, I write to you later then I intended, becauſe I thought it not fit to deliuer my opinion before manifold experience made, in a matter of ſuch worth and conſequence. <hi>Experimentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fallax,</hi> as our great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hippocrates</hi> teacheth. But now I will breefely ſhew you the vertue and excellency of your medicine. The firſt triall that I made of it, was on mine owne daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about 16. yeeres old: which for two continuall dayes, was much troubled with vomitings, keeping nothing that ſhe eat or dranke. Alſo by reaſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable inward torments ſhe could not ſleepe one winke for the ſpace of two daies and nights. In which her extremities, hauing vſed all other conuenient and commended medicines to no purpoſe, but altogether without any eaſe or mitigation of her paines, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke my ſelfe laſtly to your medicine, as to a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Anchor, and laſt hope. She tooke the ſame and kept it, and then ſlept a litle. But after 2. houres ſhe caſt againe in great abundance, and ſince ſhe hath continued perfectly well.</p>
               <p>The ſecond triall I made thereof, was vpon a very worſhipfull gentleman, <hi>Sir William Samuell</hi> Knight. He had a burning feauer, with great violence of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heat, ſo that he vtterly loſt all ſleepe: he had withall a weakeneſſe in his kidneis, and could not make wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Sundry gliſters were adminiſtred vnto him, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, vomits, and he was alſo let blood: All which (in my obſeruation) were ſo far from giuing him any eaſe, that the diſeaſe did ſtill grow ſtronger, and all the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:280:21"/> ſymptomes or accidents euery day worſe and worſe, and more grieuous. I perſwaded the giuing of your medicine. But at the firſt I could not obtaine, that he ſhould take a new and vnknowne thing. At laſt by the Importunitie of his friends, and the neceſſity of his diſeaſe ſtil increaſing, he yeelded &amp; tooke it. In an inſtant almoſt, he felt a gentle remiſſion of his heat, &amp; a milde cooling; his ſpirits comforted; his kidneis ſtrengthned, ſo that he made water in a reaſonable good quantity. Since which time, he neuer ceaſed to extoll this Medicine, though in troth, hauing beene long afflicted with a moſt violent diſeaſe, he hath not as yet fully recouered his ſtrength.</p>
               <p>The third triall I made, was vpon a maid of noble familie, which being taken with dreadfull convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, after ſome gliſters taken, had alſo this medicine, and was thereby perfectly cured.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I was deſired to ſend all the ſtore I had of this medicine, to a graue Matrone, a gentlewoman al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpent with old age, and much ſickneſſe, being then left to Gods mercy as at her laſt gaſpe. She pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the taking of this medicine, found much eaſe and comfortable ſtrength in her ſpirits, though I thinke there be no poſſible recouering her, ſo ſpent as is aforeſaid: farewell. &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>GAYTON <date>the 10. of Sept. 1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your louing friend Ioh. Markes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:280:22"/>
               <p>MAſter Doctor <hi>Anthony,</hi> though I haue no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with you at all, yet being an eye witneſſe of your generall charity extended to the whole world, in bringing to the vſe of men the moſt excellent quinteſſence for the rectifying of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the world (as I thinke) yet euer had, I am thereby imboldned to preſume of your fauour for ſome ſew graines of the ſame, which (for the ſeuerall operations that I haue ſeene thereof, in two ſpeciall friends of mine, both at the point of death) ſhall in my eſteeme for euer be held in moſt precious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt. For you ſhal vnderſtand that about a twelue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneth ſince, I came to a brother in lawes houſe of mine, one <hi>Sir William Samuell</hi> knight, of Vpton in Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton-ſhire, whom I found in great extremitie of ſickneſſe, and thereby ſo weakned with the continuall torment he was in, that all which were about him fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him greatly: he had three Doctors of Phiſicke, yet could none of them miniſter any thing to him to giue him any eaſe of his torments, but rather tormented him more, vntill at laſt, himſelfe remembred that one <hi>Mr. Markes</hi> had commended this memorable medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of yours. Which being brought, hee tooke, and it wrought ſo miraculous an effect within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of two houres, as neither he nor I euer ſaw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For it inſtantly deliuered him of his paine, which ſeemed before intollerable: It gaue him reſt, which for many daies and nights before he had bin barred of: It drew on an appetite by little and little, all meat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being loathſome vnto him: And (which is moſt maruellous) whereas formerly, by his medicines ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriating thoſe paſſages, he ſeemed to endure great torture vpon euery prouocation to the ſtoole: he had now in the day and night fiue ſtooles, and euery pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:280:22"/> was now as delightfull vnto him, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were tormenting. Then did one of his Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aduiſe, that now he ſhould take ſome Cordiall, to aſſiſt the faculties of nature being very weake. But when this was propounded vnto my brother by his wife, he vtterly refuſed it. Neuertheleſſe, it was ſo farre forth vrged, as that he tooke it, the Phyſition bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him in hand, that it was nothing elſe but Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes horne, Bezoar ſtone and ſuch like. But after taking thereof, my brother fell againe into his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tortures, and more vehement then before. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was enforced the ſelfe ſame night to ſend again vnto <hi>Mr. Markes;</hi> who releeued him as formerly he had done: ſince which time (by Gods bleſſing) he hath continued well. After this manner an obſtructed body was cured. It hath wrought a great effect in <hi>Sir Iohn Hunt</hi> Knight, of Leiceſter-Shire, who lately was very low brought with a fluxe, together with a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feuer: and being neere vnto death, and voyde of all other helpe, he was releeued by the ſelfe ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine only, and perfectly reſtored. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Doctor Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> who partly had ſeene, and partly heard theſe miraculous effects of this your Medicine, lying dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ſick at Oxford this laſt Sommer, ſent his Son in very great haſt to <hi>Maſter Markes</hi> for ſome portion of this your Medicine: his ſaid ſonne feared that at his returne, he ſhould not finde him liuing But thankes be to God, he liueth, and is well: which is to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto your Medicine, although peraduenture he will not acknowledge the ſame, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>KNIGHTHORP IN LEICESTER<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>Shire, <date>Ianuary 20. 1612.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Ready and aſſured friend, Henry Skipwith.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:280:23"/>
               <head>MACTE VIR PROBITATE, et Scientiâ ſingulari.</head>
               <p>MY wifes brother M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Skipwith,</hi> lately told me how friendly mention of me you made to him; He might very well haue reciprocated, and ſaid, how oft mention he hath heard me make of you. Yet howſoeuer, I muſt euer acknowledge my ſelfe obliged to you in double bands. For in my laſt grieuous and long languiſhing ſickneſſe, when my then Phyſition <hi>Dr. C.</hi> ſtaggered in his Iudgement of my Diſeaſe, and in the hope of my recouery he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to quaile: yea when my ſelfe, and all my behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders did deſpaire of my life; then by Gods prouidence, a friend (telling the rare vertues of your <hi>Aurum Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile</hi>) cauſed two graines of the ſame, to be diſſolued in fiue ſpoonfuls of diſtilled Endiue Water, and ſo to be miniſtred vnto me. After receiuing thereof, within one houres ſpace, it is incredible to be ſpoken, what alleuiation I found of my languiſhings, and what cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboration of all my vitall parts. In the morning I tooke it, and vntill night I felt a moſt happy operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. It procured ſtooles all that day, ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly as my ſoule could deſire: vntil ſuch time as that my Phyſition (after he had taken his leaue of me for that night, I that I had now compoſed my ſelf to reſt) came againe vnto me, hauing vpon the point of a knife ſomewhat which hee did put into my mouth, being then almoſt aſleepe. But about midnight when I did awake, I found my ſelfe relapſed as before. Then, vtterly deſpairing of my life, I called (as I
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:280:23"/> thought my laſt call) vnto my wife, intreating her to ſend againe to my foreſaid friend, to intreate him to conſider, whether in his Iudgement two graines were not too ſmal a proportion to ouercome the maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſo dangerous a Diſeaſe. He therefore gaue me this ſecond time three graines, which ſpeedily as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and wonderfully did refreſh my ſpirits, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by my bodie was very ſoluble for the ſpace of 7. daies after. And notwithſtanding ſundry euacuations eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, my ſtrength daily increaſed. Then was that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. exceedingly angry that I did entertaine his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell no longer: ſince which time he hath wrote an Engliſh booke, vncharitably defaming me, and cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt that famous Medicine, which by the prouidence of God reſtored vnto me both life and health. Now concerning the chiefe intention of theſe my letters, I pray you ſend me 12. graines of your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table gold in ſuch forme as my brother M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Henry Skipwith</hi> lately receiued from you. This bearer my friend ſhall giue you ſatisfaction for the ſame, &amp;c. The Author of health is God, who perpetually preſerue you, vnto whome he hath vouchſafed ſuch fauour as to attaine vnto ſo great a reſtorer of health, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longer of life, as this <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> appeareth to be. Farewell. Reu. Dr.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Vpton, <date>15. Feb. 1612.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your moſt louing friend William Samuell.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:280:24"/>
               <p>VVOrthy Sir. I am aduiſed by that Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Doctor, Maſter Doctor <hi>Hunton,</hi> in theſe parts highly accounted, to require in behalfe of our worthy friend, a knight, your helpe and aduice, in a deplored eſtate, wherein hee now ſtandeth. We deſire alſo ſome quantity of your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Potabile,</hi> with direction for the due adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof. This gentleman diſeaſed is neere 80 yeares of age, of Cholericke conſtitution. The firſt originall of his Infirmitie (as we coniecture) was by company of his wife being yong. Not long after in a Iourney which he tooke, when he was yet ſcarſe ſixe myles from his houſe, he was conſtrained oft times for to alight from his horſe. Then did he make water, and in his water either blood, or ſome ſubſtance like vnto blood, peraduenture ſpermaticall, which hath continued now many daies. Alſo euen to this time he is vnable to retaine his vrine, by the Imbecillitie of his bladder as wee ſuppoſe. A Gonorrhe likewiſe he was ſubiect vnto. He is not as yet free from any of theſe Infirmities. We expect ſome helpe from you. For your charges and counſell, this gentleman will giue you full content. My ſelfe alſo will be with you this next Terme, and will not be vnthankfull.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Trent <date>the 11. of Sept. 1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your moſt louing friend, N. W. Phyſition.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:280:24"/>
               <p>MAſter Doctor <hi>Anthony</hi> you may call to minde,<note place="margin">This letter came from the Knight himſelfe.</note> if you pleaſe, that about September laſt paſt, you wrote certaine letters vnto me. At which time I alſo receiued from you fiue ounces of your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Potabile,</hi> to the praiſe of God, your commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and my great good. My Diſeaſes were mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the former letters. Beſides which I had alſo a great ſwelling from my hucchlebone vnto the ſoles of my feete. But it is without paine: peraduenture it came of cold, or with lying long time vpon my right ſide. I vnderſtand by Maſter <hi>Doctor Hunton,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> which you ſent me, you haue alſo the ſubſtance of gold in forme like hony, I pray you ſend me thereof, and the manner how to vſe the ſame. I doe feele (I praiſe God) a mitigation of all my paines and Infirmities throughout all my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: the ſwelling which I mentioned doth daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: My vrine alſo I am able to retaine. This booke of yours Maſter <hi>Doctor Hunton</hi> requeſted of me. Send me an other I pray you, your ſtudies and endeauours God alwaies bleſſe: farewell.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>BLYBROVVGH <date>Octob. 10. 1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your friend. H. A.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:280:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis gentleman, of whom I ſhall now next write, and whoſe letters ſent vnto me are extant, being Secretarie to the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouable the Earle of Southampton, in his owne words had beene long ſicke of a Quartane feuer: for Cure whereof he entertained a moſt learned Phyſition, who miniſtred vnto him a long time ſuch Medicines as were appropriate: Neither yet had he ouermaſtered the feuer; nor reſtored any ſtrength vnto the patient. Then did this Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition perſwade this gentleman his patient to vſe my Aurum Potabile; which he did, and with good ſucceſſe. Whereupon, he wrote afterwards vnto me for more thereof, as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, I haue found ſo much good vſe of your <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> as makes me deſire more. For I muſt truely ſay, I haue gotten much ſtrength ſince I tooke it, and recouered my ſpirits exceedingly decaied by extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſickneſſe: my ſtore is not ſo ſpent, but that I haue ſome left in the Country, but my ſlay hath bin longer here then I expected; and therfore may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied from you with more eaſe then from thence. Which I deſire may be ſent by this bearer of the beſt: So ſhall I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very louing friend, Thomas Kisley.</signed>
                  <dateline>SOVTHAMPTON HOVSE <date>THIS 26. of Nouemb. 1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:280:25"/>
               <p>MAſter <hi>Doctor Anthony,</hi> I pray you make me ſo much beholding vnto you as to beſtow me this twentie ſhillings in that ſoueraigne quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence which I had of you at my being with you. For (as I told you) I was to haue but one of thoſe glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes my ſelfe: which, one of my eſpeciall friends hath had of me; ſo that now, I haue ſcarcely one graine left. <hi>Sir Brian Caue Knight,</hi> was taken with a violent burning feuer: but after taking of this Medicine, he had only one fit, and then was perfectly well recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Alſo a ſeruant of mine, had in like manner ſo dangerous a Feuer, that at my comming home I found him at point of death. The onely taking of this Medicine hath ſo purged him by an extraordinary Sweat, (that thankes be to God) he is at this time in a Iourney abroad with me, and finds his bodie in ſo good temper as it was not of a Twelue moneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your aſſured friend to vſe Henry Skipwith.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:280:26"/>
               <p>SIr. Some few houres after your departure, Maſter Doct. <hi>Lewknar</hi> came hither to my Lord Biſhop of Wincheſter. And at ſupper, after my Lord had made ſome relation of the proceedings and benefite he found of your <hi>Aurum Potabile, Doctor Lewknar</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in the comendation therof, ſaying; That on Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday laſt paſt, he being at Cowdry, came to a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman who was dead to the world, being both ſpeechleſſe and knowing no body; he gaue her one ſpoonfull of your <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> in that caſe as ſhee then was. And at the firſt taking thereof, ſhe fell into ſtrange convulſions, wherein ſhe continued two houres: and after he gaue her as much more, and then ſhe fell into a great ſweat: and 2 houres after, he gaue her a ſpoonfull more, &amp; ſhe fell into a fine ſleepe, and waking ſhe ſaid, Giue me more of that: which was done; and ſhe tooke good reſt after. And the next day, he went to ſee how ſhe did, and found her eating of a Chicken. This he told before my <hi>Lord Biſhop,</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Doctor Steward</hi> of the Arches, <hi>Sir Thomas Bilſon</hi> my Lords ſonne, and my ſelfe.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>WALTHAM <date>THIS 15. of Auguſt 1611.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your louing friend Tho. Webbes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:280:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>THis Doctor Lewknar, of whom mention is made in theſe former letters, did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards write vnto me, deſiring to haue more of my Potable gold. For this learned Gentleman, had before found and ſeene the effects thereof in the Cure of his daughter in law by marriage with his Sonne, being ſtrongly taken with the falling ſickneſſe. The caſe whereof ſet downe in a part of his letter to me, which I haue ſhewed in the end of my firſt booke. Whereupon the aduerſaries both to my ſelfe and the truth, haue greatly accuſed (I was about to ſay ſlandered him) as may appeare by an other letter of his ſent vnto me beginning thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good <hi>Doctor Anthony,</hi> I haue beene bitterly taxed, for giuing teſtimony of the good ſucceſſe of your <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum potabile:</hi> which doth nothing at all daunt me. For I aſſure my ſelfe, that <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> being rightly made (which few haue attained vnto) is a ſingular medicine howſoeuer, I thinke yours (as I haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced) to be good. And therefore I pray you ſend me two ounces by this my kinſman, and write vnto me, what effect it worketh in womens monethly courſes, &amp;. <hi>And after it foloweth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I doe aſſuredly promiſe you, that as I ſhall find the effect thereof good, all the Societie of the Colledge ſhall not auert me. So likewiſe, ſhall not any priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of friendſhip, flattery or gaine, induce me at any time, to giue approbation to any dangerous or vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine medicine, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your louing friend George Lewknar.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:280:27"/>
               <p>I Doubt not (my good Coſen) but you much deſire to heare what effects your <hi>Auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Potabile</hi> hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in theſe parts. A certaine neere neighbour of mine, the wife of <hi>Ro. Downing,</hi> lay euen at point of death, after a long languiſhing ſickneſſe (for ſhee was prayed for in the Church.) Whereupon, my Sonne <hi>Barners</hi> &amp; I, went in the after noone to ſee her. Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after our comming, ſhe tooke a potion of a Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there preſent, which ſodainly ſhe caſt vp: at which I muſed. Then did her husband affirme, that for the ſpace of a moneth before, ſhe had not taken downe a ſpoonfull of any thing, but ſhe did likewiſe caſt it vp. My Son did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> importune me, to giue her a ſpoonful of your <hi>Aurum potabile;</hi> which I was very loath to doe, ſeeing ſhe ſeemed but a dead woman: and, it might be ſome diſcredit to the medicine, &amp; to me. Yet at the laſt I did yeeld, ſhe being deſirous thereof: I gaue her ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſpoonfull, which ſtaied with her contrary to all our expectations. And within a ſhort time, whereas before ſhe was ſo cold, that they were forced to lay more cloathes on her, ſhe came to a kind naturall heat. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we gaue her ſome mace-ale with <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> which ſhe digeſted, and afterwards mace-ale alone, which alſo ſtaied with her. The 3. day after, we ſent to viſit her, who ſent vs word that the ſame day ſhe had eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beſt part of a Chicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; did hope to come to vs ſhortly, &amp;c. You ſhall alſo know that Mr. <hi>Boſwell</hi> a Miniſter &amp; Preacher of <hi>Saffron Walden,</hi> did greatly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune me for one ounce of <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> for his wife, being accounted paſt Cure in a languiſhing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. And ſhe by that onely ounce receiued ſo much comfort, that he ſent vp to Lond. to you for more, &amp;c</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>COVVLING, <date>21. die Maij. 1611</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your aſſured louing Coſen Tho. Wolridge, Iuſtice of peace in Eſſex.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:280:27"/>
               <p>A <hi>Letter ſent to Maſter Edward Smith of the Temple, Counſellor at the common lawes, from Maſter George Wethery, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to the right honourable the Lord Shef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, Lord Preſident of his Maieſties Councell eſtabliſhed for the North parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good <hi>Maſter Smith,</hi> my Lord would haue you ſend preſently to <hi>Doctor Anthony,</hi> and deſire him to ſend his Lordſhip (with all poſſible ſpeed) the like quantity of his <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> as he ſent the laſt time; for that my Lord hath made many trials of it, and will report much good thereof; which will turne greatly to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Doctors aduantage, and the credit of his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Yorke <date>this 30. of Septemb. 1613.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Alwaies yours George Wethery.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A <hi>True Relation made by me Elias Holmes, of the manifold vertues of Maſter Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Anthonies Aurum Potabile, tryed by the command of the right honourable, Edmund Lord Sheffield, Lord Preſident of Yorke.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:280:28"/>
               <p>THe wife of <hi>Iohn Goulſbrough</hi> ſeruant to my Lord, lay very ſicke ſundry daies before my Lord had knowledge thereof. Then was I ſent vnto her, whom I found languiſhing and in great extremitie. Shee was greatly ſweld in her bodie, and had alſo a looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that it paſt from her almoſt vnknowing to her. And further ſhe was greatly diſtempered in heat. She had taken no manner ſuſtenance for 4. or 5. daies before, whereby ſhee was growne ſo weake, that ſhee could not mooue her body but as ſhe was helpt by others. Alſo her eyes were greatly ſwelled: her ſpeech could not be heard the length of the bed: ſhee deſired nothing but drinke, taking no reſt, neither night nor day.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſpoonfull that I gaue her, did ſhew ſmall effect whilſt I was with her, which was ſome houre: but they which attended her, ſaid, that ſome two houres after, it made her riſt, and to voide a little wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her Stomacke. At euening I gaue her one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpoonfull, and before I could ſeale vp the glaſſe, ſhe was in a little ſlumber, but it continued not long. Neuertheleſſe, ſhee felt ſo much eaſe at her Stomack, that ſhe ſaid, What is this that my good Lord hath ſent me: for I giue God thankes I feele much eaſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that I did: with that ſhe prayed hartily for my Lord And both her ſpeech and countenance ſeemed better then before: Then about one of the clock at midnyght, ſhe fell aſleepe, and ſlept two houres. The next morning, I gaue her the third ſpoonfull; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſhe caſt a little, and in her caſting ſhe tooke cold, which cauſed her to cough, and made her ſo ill and weake, that I thought my laboure was all loſt. Her looſenes alſo held her ſtill. But it pleaſed God to giue ſuch a bleſſing vnto this Medicine, that after the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:280:28"/> taking of 4. or 5. ſpoonfull more, her flux was ſtaide, her ſtrength alſo recouered in ſuch ſort, that ſhe was able to ſit vpright in her bed, and to receiue ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Alſo, after three ſpoonful more, ſhee could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to haue her clothes put on, and with a little helpe, to walke vp and downe the Chamber. Shee tooke in all 13. ſpoonfuls. Then did ſhe acknowledge that ſhee was perfectly well, giuing God thankes therefore: And to me ſhee ſaid, Now <hi>Maſter Holmes</hi> I pray you ſpare your further labour, &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <hi>THomas Taylor,</hi> one of my Lords houſhold ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, about the ſame time in the former yeere had an extraordinary Maligne feuer &amp; of long<note place="margin">A quotidian maligne feuer.</note> continuance. He was a very able and ſtrong man: Neuertheleſſe, it had ſo weakned him, that he was ſeantly able to goe vpright: He could endure to take no ſuſtenance for a long time. Often times alſo as a mad man, he would ariſe out of his bed in the night ſeaſon, and lye downe on the floore, and there lie, vntill ſome body came by chance to helpe him.</p>
                  <p>This yeare he likewiſe fell into the ſame Infirmity by all ſignes and tokens. His firſt fit continued ſixe houres, with ſuch violent paine at his heart, that he was enforced to cry out. My Lord was not willing that I ſhould giue him any thing this firſt fit. The next day after, when the former paſſions began to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault him, my Lord ſent me vnto him, and I gaue him one ſpoonfull of this Medicine. After which, he did ſundry times caſt vp by vomit, a very filthy and euill ſubſtance. When he had done caſting, I gaue him another ſpoonfull, and ſo he reſted quietly, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing an eaſie fit which continued the ſpace of three
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:280:29"/> houres. His third fit came alſo vnto him, then I gaue him one other ſpoonfull, and within a quarter of an houre, he had a vomit. I gaue him one other ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and he had one other vomit. I gaue him then an other, that is, three times one after an other, and three times he vomited: and then he was prouoked to the ſtoole. Whilſt he was there, he had againe a very great vomit, being of diuers colors, and a mucilage or ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie ſubſtance. After this vomit, I gaue him one other ſpoonfull, and then he ſlept quietly, and had no more fits afterward.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEnry Kickinſon</hi> one of my Lords ſeruants, it<note place="margin">A continuall maligne feuer.</note> pleaſed God to viſite with an extraordinary Quotidian feuer, hauing a ſenſible paine in his bones, which made him ſo ſore that he could not abide one to touch him: and with the extremitie thereof, became euen mad and ſenſeleſſe, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any man. Alſo ſo weake, that euery one of his friends expected death. He continued in this extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie a fortnight, before I was ſent to him: In which time, he had taken little ſuſtenance. His body alſo was extreamely hot, and he tooke no reſt.</p>
                  <p>After the firſt ſpoonfull that I gaue him, within halfe an houre he fell aſleepe, and ſlept the ſpace of one houre, and when he awoke did caſt a little. At night I gaue him one other ſpoonfull after which he ſlept two houres, and then ſpake theſe words. Will not <hi>Maſter Holmes</hi> come againe vnto me? and other ſuch like ſpeaches manifeſtly approouing that he had found comfort by that which I had giuen him. Then did he giue thankes vnto God. All that I gaue him was eleuen ſpoonfuls. So by little and little he amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and became perfectly recouered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:280:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAny others I could here ſet downe, which haue receiued in theſe parts preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe by this Medicine. Among the reſt, my Lords Children both ſonnes and Daughters, who ſundry times and in ſundry caſes being affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, haue alwaies bene cured with this onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. Alſo my Lord himſelfe by vſe thereof, doth preuent many ſits of the Stone which heretofore he hath beene ſubiect vnto, and preſerueth his health thereby; So likewiſe doth my Lady.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>LAſtly for my ſelfe, being ſubiect vnto an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame migrim in my head, as Phyſitions call it, but my diſeaſe is in this manner. Many times in the yeare, being in perfect health, I ſhall haue my ſight ſodenly taken away; ſo ſhall I continue halfe an houre: then ſhall I haue a moſt violent aking in my head, alſo a ſleepineſſe; then a kind of ſtupor firſt in my lips and tongue, and ſo it goeth downe to my hands; I ſtretch them out like vnto the <hi>Palſey,</hi> and<note place="margin">A dead Palſey</note> thus it holds me a good while: Then it will go downe into my legs. All this while I ſhall haue a great deſire to caſt, but cannot, vntill I haue beene in this fit ſome 6. houres: and then with much adoe I ſhall caſt, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter once or twice caſting I ſhall haue ſome better eaſe. As long as I am in that former extremitie, I ſhall ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſarcely be able to fetch my breath, neither to ſpeake, nor vnderſtand, nor heare what is ſpoken. But
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:280:30"/> at the laſt I fall aſleepe, &amp; then I begin to be wel, &amp; yet not very wel, nor in perfect good health for the ſpace of one whole weeke after. Now it pleaſed God, that being at Lond. in Decem. laſt, 1613. being in preſence of my Lord, ſuddenly I felt that my ſight failed me, my head aked, and that my fit approached neere. Whereupon I craued pardon of my Lord, being not able to goe forward with his buſineſſe that I had then in hand. My Lord therefore commanded mee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to take ſome <hi>Aurum Potabile;</hi> for it was then in my cuſtodie. But I made the mixture ſomewhat more effectuall of the gold, then I was accuſtomed to doe at other times. And within one quarter of an houre after taking thereof, my ſpirits and ſenſes were comforted: the cold, which at the firſt poſſeſſed me, became temperate. Alſo I brake winde both vpward and downward. Likewiſe I had a deſire to vomit, and an inclination to ſleepe: But my Lord would not permit me, cauſing me to bee kept walking vp and downe. Whereby after the ſpace of one houre I felt my ſelfe very well: only my head did ake a little. But (praiſed be God) I did not fall into my vſuall fits. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, by taking that <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> I became looſe bodied, whereas vſually I am accuſtomed to be bound. All theſe things (if neede require) I will bee ready vpon mine oath to auouch. Thus I doe end.</p>
                  <p>EVER SINCE I TOOKE THIS Medicine I haue continued in good health, praiſed be God.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Feb. 4. 1614.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your louing friend Elias Holmes, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my foreſaid Lord in his Chamber.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:280:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I May not forget here to remember the right Reuerend father in God, whoſe learning, pietie and vertue be ſufficiently knowne, the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Wincheſter, my Honourable good Patron: againſt whoſe teſtimonie there can be no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. His Lordſhip is a moſt autenticke witneſſe of this my Potable gold, and teſtifieth the vertues thereof to all perſons: and can (if neede require) maintaine the ſame to the greateſt perſons of this Realme: how not onely himſelfe in the recouerie and maintenance of his owne bodily health, much weakened with continuall ſtudies, and the late great paines in conference of many copies, for the true tranſlation of the holy Scriptures out of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew into Engliſh: but alſo very many others, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Aurum Potabile from his pious charitie, haue beene from many and diuers diſeaſes recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and reſtored to their former health by vſe thereof. But becauſe the vocall and liuely atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of his Lordſhip, can more ſatisfie any that require ſatisfaction, then any deliuery by his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſent me, I will be ſparing in that point: and trouble the Reader onely with a few of many, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how, and to whome, his Lordſhip in greateſt neceſſities, and dangerous diſeaſes, did liberally beſtow this Potable gold, and commanded the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof to be briefely ſet downe, as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:280:31"/>
                  <p>SIr, being appointed by my Lord &amp; Mr. to confer with diuers of this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, who haue bin cured of ſundry diſeaſes with <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> giuen vnto them by his Lordſhip: I haue accordingly take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the report of thoſe few that were neere this place, and with whom I might conueniently ſpeake. Many more there are, that receiued good by it, which dwell remote from this place, with whom I ſhall ſpeake as occaſion ſhall be offered, and leiſure permit to do it. So hoping to be better furniſhed with theſe things againſt your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into Hampſhire, which is ſhortly expected, I take leaue, reſting,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your aſſured friend to my power, Antho. Langford Secretary to my Lord Biſhop of Wincheſter.</signed>
                     <dateline>BISHOPS WATHAM <date>THE laſt of Nouember, 1612.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>GOod Sir, although it be vnuſuall with me to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer exchange of words to ſtrangers, yet ſince the heauenly prouidence hath deſigned a part of noble skill, wherein I vnderſtand you are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, to be ſome meanes of healthfull vſe vnto me, I ſhould hold it a iuſt forfeit of my recouered eſtate, if I ſhould ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce any thing that appertaineth to the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it. I therefore cannot chooſe but tell you how
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:280:31"/> much I am bound to my Honourable good Lord of Wincheſter, who firſt of his good fauour vouchſafed me of your <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> ſo well agreeing with my diſeaſed body, as that I ſhall become a Cuſtomer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you for more of it. I find it very milde aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phyſicke in operation, cauſing a temperate ſweat, and much allaying the violence of the offending hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors. How highly I doe prize it, this my letter ſhall be hoſtage: deſiring him from whoſe vnſearchable power the vertue comes, to bleſſe you for it, to whoſe further grace I leaue you; and reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your aſſured friend Lucy Ieruice, wife vnto Sir Tho. Ieruice knight.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>I Was ſicke of an ague ſome ſeuen night or there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts,<note place="margin">A malignant burning feuer.</note> &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had two ſuch fits, as I &amp; all that did ſee me, thought I could not haue eſcaped death. Then I dranke a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> in the middle of mine extreame burning, and within a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of one houre after, the extreame paine in my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke ceaſed, and I felt my ſelfe very well. Only the heat remained with me about one houre, which paine of the ſtomacke was wont to hold me 3. or 4. houres in the former fits. The next day that my Ague ſhould come, it came not all the day, vntill ſupper time. And ſitting at ſupper, it came very terribly vpon me, ſo that I was driuen to go to bed. I was extremely ſick. Then I called for a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> and it wrought with me as it did before. I did alſo ſweat ſome three houres, and ſo I thanke God, he tooke his farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:280:32"/>
               <p>SIr, the Diſeaſe of my Sonne was in this manner:<note place="margin">A long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian with a vomiting.</note> It tooke him once in 24. houres, with a colde ſhiuering in the likeneſſe of an Ague. Which colde helde him but a ſhort time. Afterward, he fell into an extreame heate, with a vomiting which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about 3. or 4. houres. In this manner he was daily perplexed the ſpace of a Moneth or fiue weekes, before he tooke the <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi> Which at the firſt taking, being at the beginning of his cold, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his vomiting, and his fit was not ſo extreme as it had beene before. And in this manner he tooke it 3. or 4. fits immediately one after another, about the quantitie of a ſpoonful or ſomewhat leſſe: and ſtill his fits did leſſon and decay, and laſtly left him altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Durlay <date>Ianuary 10. 1612.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Francis Forteſcue.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:280:32"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE COL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LECTION AND <hi>RELATION OF</hi> THOSE FEW AMONGST MANY, <hi>THAT HAVE TAKEN AVRVM</hi> POTABILE, IN THIS COVNTY of SOVTHAMPTON, truly related concerning the effect thereof, deliuered <hi>from their owne mouthes vnto me</hi> Anthony Langford.</head>
            <div type="account">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Homas Wheeler</hi> of Waltham hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, aged 67. yeares, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſicke the ſpace of one moneth of a new diſeaſe very common at that time, whereof many died. This man likewiſe was in ſo great perill of death<note place="margin">An aged man at point of death.</note> that the bell tolled for him, and he was prayed for in the Church. In this his deſperate caſe, a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> was giuen vnto him, by which he felt ſome preſent releefe, and fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a gentle Sweat for an houre or twaine: Then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one other ſpoonfull, he ſlept quietly the ſpace of an houre: After that a third ſpoonfull, by which he had a vomit of a great quantity of ſlymie humors. And by ſenſible degrees he recouered health, praiſed be God, and is yet lyuing being of great yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:280:33"/>
               <p>EDmund Laurence of Biſhops Waltham gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">A continuall burning feuer</note> aged 36. yeares, was perplexed with a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feuer continuing two daies, and two nights without intermiſſion; he onely tooke one ſpoonful or rather leſſe in quantity of the <hi>Aurum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabile,</hi> and by degrees he ſoone returned into his for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer temper and health againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>GIles Ethericke Yeoman of the ſame place, 40.<note place="margin">A continuall and ſharp bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feuer.</note> yeares of age, had a continuall and ſharpe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning feuer eight daies and nights. In all which time he could take no reſt: he tooke two ſpoonfuls of <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> and ſlept quietly the ſpace of two houres the ſame night. The next day towards euening, taking the like quantitie, he ſlept the whole night quietly, and recouered perfect health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>VVIlliam Hilles of Waltham aforeſaid, Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">A quotidian.</note> aged 55. yeares, hauing had fiue fits of a quotidian, and beeing entred into the ſixt, he tooke a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> which put him out of his colde fit, and made him ſweat; and then taking as much more, it gaue him a good vomit and 2. or 3. ſtooles: and thereupon ſhortly after hee ſlept quietly and recouered his ſtomacke, which both had failed him the former 5. daies, and ſince he hath beene well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:280:33"/>
               <p>IOhn Walter of the ſame, 40. yeares of age, hauing<note place="margin">A tertian fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</note> had 4. fits of a Tertian, and the fift fit being vpon him, he tooke a good ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi> Whereupon within one houre after, his fit left him, and neuer troubled him ſince.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Iohn Walter,</hi> hauing 2. ſpoonfuls of <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> left, after he himſelfe was cured, he gaue the ſame vnto a maide in Hambleton of 14. yeares, who<note place="margin">A tertian.</note> had languiſhed of a tertian feuer a quarter of a yeare before, and thereby was cured and had no more fits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>HEnry Hindle of Waltham, 47. yeares aged, for<note place="margin">A continuall feuer with vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting.</note> the ſpace of fiue daies continually had a feuer without intermiſſion. He could not retaine any thing in all that time, that he did either eate or drinke. After the fift day, he tooke a ſpoonfull of the <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> which he did not caſt vp as his other nutriments: but digeſted it, and it put him into a ſweat that continued about 4. houres: Then againe he tooke as much more, and did ſweat 3. houres more: After that he aroſe, and being vp, he did vomit a pint of thicke viſcous flegme. Then after the ſpace of two houres, he did eate of a peece of veale, which he retained and digeſted. And the next day went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and in ſhort time recouered his former health which he inioyeth now.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:280:34"/>
               <p>IOhn Cole of Waltham Mercer, 43. yeares aged,<note place="margin">A Paſſion of the heart.</note> was grieued with an extreame paine at his heart, ſo that for the ſpace of three daies he could neither take foode nor reſt, and was growne ſo weake, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man doubted his life. A ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabile</hi> was giuen him by thoſe about him, hee not knowing what they gaue him. And after one houre, an other ſpoonfull; and a while after the third ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. By this meanes, he continued long in a ſweat, and within two daies after was reſtored to health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <p>THeſe alſo whoſe names are vnder written, haue all in their extremitie of ſickneſſe, receiued <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> from my Lord Biſhop, and are well recouered: But hetherto I haue had no conference with them. Howbeit it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that by meanes thereof, they were recouered from ſundry dangerous Infirmities.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Moore Maſter of Arts, of this new feuer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reuben Hamme gent. the like.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The wife of Mr. Armwood in the foreſt, of the like.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The wife of Mr. Cotton of Roche Court.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The wife of Iohn Hawkeſworth, cured of a ſtrange diſeaſe, whereof ſhee had long before languiſhed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Peckham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho. Beale, about one hundred yeares of age, and recouered of this new ague, and is yet liuing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Searle of Northampton gent. hauing long languiſhed of this new ague.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nicholas Prior.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Anthony Langford.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="accounts">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:280:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Doubt not but that theſe Teſtimonies ſo war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted, being but a few exemplarie proofes of very many, will ſatisfie any vnderſtanding and honeſt reader. I intend not with a whole Calender or endleſſe Catalogue, and with tedious reading of the ſame thing often done, to weary the reader. Elſe I could eaſily inlarge this Roule: It being certaine, that there is ſcarce any one Shire or Lordſhip in England, from whence I haue not bin ſent vnto, for my potable gold, with which, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, gentlemen, and perſons of other rankes haue bin diuerſly cured and releeued, in their neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their healths: Apparent it is, that it neuer hurt any, profited all, though all haue not recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. We muſt herein euer acknowledge the vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed ordinance of God, not to bee controlled by any Art or Induſtrie of humane Remedies. I deſire therefore the patient Indifferencie of all Readers, to conſider and fauourably to Interpret theſe my proceedings. For I acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that in ordinary Cures performed, no Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Phyſition ought to print the Calender of his ſucceſſes, except in ſome cure and peculiar caſe, which ſeldome happening, may be a light and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to others (though many haue ſought fame thereby) which was farre from my intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. But the neceſſitie of vindicating my integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the well knowne truth of the effects of my potable gold, haue made that neceſſarily volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which before I neuer entertained in priuate conſultation. For good wine needs no Buſh or
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:280:35"/> Signe. And theſe be the motiues why I offer this ſmall aſſay (I hope not weariſome to be read and obſerued) beeing a ſhort mention of ſome perſons and Diſeaſes, which haue receiued preſent helpe by the vſe of this ſo maligned Medicine: (my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table gold) I ſay, a ſhort mention, not of all, nor the greater part, nor in any neere proportion of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to the totall. For ſome will not conſent to bee named: and ſome ſpecialties may not be diuulged. And in ſome reſpect I am not very forward of mine owne nature to enlarge the malice of my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, by publiſhing ſome Cures which cannot pleaſe them to heare of. Thus farre forth concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning other mens teſtimonies: I will proceede to mine owne practiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>AS the brighter the Sunne is, the more apparent be the ſhadowes cauſed by ſolid &amp; thicke duskiſh bodies: ſo, the more excellent &amp; famous the glorie is, that is atchieued by things wel &amp; faithfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; the more it is ſpurgald with the kicking heeles of Enuie. As this is true in all actions and commercements of this life, ſo it hath notoriouſly and lauiſhly bin practiſed againſt me in my proceedings. At the very firſt, this corroding ſpite, ſparing no man, this malicious detraction, enemie of truth, ſet vp their whole reſt in ſuch faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as they could, to demoliſh my faire buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. But truth, that precious daughter of time, hath now vndertaken the quarrell,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:280:35"/> that will ſay, nill they, ſhee muſt and will preuaile againſt their furie, and maintaine her quiet nauigation, notwithſtanding any guſtes or ſtormes, from their dry, and water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Clowdes. And to the intent that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnpartiall, vnpreiudiced, and Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent reader, may the better vnderſtand the cauſe of theſe Impreſſions, and the ſtate and firſt force of this controuerſie, which hath now enforced the publike atteſtation of the vertues of this Medicine: I will as briefely and ſparingly as may be, by one or two Inſtances, declare the firſt originall cauſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>SIr <hi>Adolfe Cary</hi> a worthy knight, nobly deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, being not well, ſent for a Phyſition of great name &amp; fame: who gaue him ſuch Medicines as he thought fit, one being a Purgation, which did not only clenſe the firſt veines, but wrought ſomewhat forceably. Within ſhort time after, the diſeaſe was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered to be the ſmall Pocks. But by the vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble revulſion and indraught of that ſo ſtrong Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as I thinke) and peraduenture by ſome other neglect, nature failed in the ſufficient expulſion of the puſtules. Alſo thoſe exitures which appeared, ſhortly after ſunke againe, or, as we commonly ſay, went in. Hereupon, the Patient fell into that extremitie, that the eminent perill of his life could not be hid, ſo that all they that were about him deſpaired vtterly of his recouery. Wherefore they ſent to his brother, to call haſtily for the Doctors beſt accquainted with the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:280:36"/> ſtate of his body, which were two: Who miſſing them both, neither knowing where to ſeeke either of them, and being very ſenſible and heauy for his brothers deſperate caſe, by chance met with me in the way, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats me to accompany him to his brother, then ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangerouſly ſicke. But I hearing the names of thoſe Doctors, was vnwilling to goe, being loth to giue offence: alſo that gentleman was at that time vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnknowne vnto me, whereby the rather I excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my ſelfe. He replied, that I was ſufficiently knowne to him by a friend of his whom I had cured, and therefore inſtantly perſiſted, that in ſo honeſt and neceſſary and iuſt a cauſe I would not refuſe him. I conſented, went with him; and being then euening I viſited the ſicke gentleman his brother, and found him in a moſt deplorable ſtate, without ſleepe or any other reſt, raging and rauing. He tooke a ſpoonfull of my <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> with which he preſently became quiet, of a more cheerefull countenance, and fell into a gentle ſleepe. After one houre I gaue him an other ſpoonfull, after which he ſpake aduiſedly, &amp; ſaid he was much comforted, &amp; ſo ſleept again, &amp; ſweat natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally al his body ouer. And (which was the beſt ſigne) the Pocks or Puſtuls did againe come out plentifully. I attended him all that night, &amp; at fit &amp; ſeaſonable times gaue him my medicine, ſometime pure of it ſelfe, ſometimes mixed with broth or other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient liquor. The next morning, one of his firſt Doctors comming &amp; finding me there with his patient, tooke that for his occaſion to raile on me in vnſeeming termes. To whom it was anſwered, that I was vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and almoſt compulſiuely brought thither, by the neereſt of blood to the ſick gentleman, &amp; with no leſſe intreaty then others. But theſe Phyſitians were
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:280:36"/> ſo far from conferring with me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the further health of this patient, whom they then found in very good caſe, that they both ioyned, and would not bee quiet, before they had rid me thence; contrary to the will of the patient, and of thoſe that were preſent. In what caſe and ſtate I both found and left this gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, you haue hard. After my departure, what coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or aſtringent, or otherwiſe qualified Syrupes, or Electuaries, or other forme of medicine they gaue him all that day I know not. But this I know, that the next night he relapſed into the ſame cruell and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate accidents, in which I formerly had found him, and from which I had reſtored him: peraduenture, he fell into this relaps for want of that my medicine, ſo powrefull in ſtrengthning the heart, and expelling poyſon from it. For doubtleſſe, the exitures being ſtopped, and the poyſon returning from the outward parts of the body, whither nature had expelled it, to the heart, the ſame accidents muſt needes returne. Such relapſes are moſt dangerous, becauſe both the infection is ſtronger, and the body weaker. And ſo it appeared in this noble gentleman, by this his vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly death. Then did theſe Phyſitions vnder whoſe hands he died, bethinke themſelues of ſome ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme, to avoid the imputation imminent. One of them therefore haſtneth to the Court, where he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth excuſe of himſelfe, and accuſation of me. And further cauſeth me to bee cited to the Colledge of London Phyſitions, and with the eloquence of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus</hi> very ſtoutly accuſeth me, as culpable of the death of this gentleman. Where I acquited my ſelfe, and maintained my innocency by foure lawfull witneſſes, ſeruants and attendants of their late Maſter the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed knight: Who with one conſent and conteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:280:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:280:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:280:38"/> dilated: That I came to their ſaid Maſter lying in his laſt and extreame pangs, rauing after the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the ſmall pocks were ſtriken in: That after I had with carefull and diligent attendance all that night adminiſtred my potable Gold vnto him, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, the extremities of his paſſions, and grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of accidents were much eaſed and abated, he more quiet and in better ſenſe, and that the Puſtules of his diſeafe did againe plentifully breake out, by which meanes he was reſpectiuely in good temper: And that the next day when the ſaid Phyſitions had excluded me, and giuen him their mixtures, all things turned to their old courſe, he to his former extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo died. His Maieſtie alſo had commanded 4. honourable perſons to be preſent at the Colledge in the hearing and debating of theſe actions now in queſtion: that is, the right honourable the Lord <hi>Kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, Sir Henry</hi> and <hi>Sir Philip Cary</hi> knights, brethren of <hi>Sir Adolph</hi> deceaſed, and <hi>Sir William Godolphin</hi> knight; who finding it fully proued, how I found him (in the agony of death) how I left him (in good temper) how the other Doctors receiued him (in very good caſe for that diſeaſe) how they left him (dead,) truly reported the whole matter to the Kings Maieſtie as indeede it was. What his Maieſties cenſure then was herein, and on whom he would lay this imputation of his death, may eaſily be coniectured out of the manifeſtations of the cauſe. Alſo thoſe two worthy brethren, meere ſtrangers to me at that time, liuing in honourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and place, ſo generouſly and vertuouſly, that none dare entertaine any ſiniſter thought againſt their ſinceritie; nor opinion that they will for any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whatſoeuer be induced to report any vntruth for me nor any other: are alwaies ready to giue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:280:38"/> ſatisfaction, if any as yet be not ſufficiently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of theſe proceedings. Reaſon it ſelfe, in one maine ground of Phyſicall indications doth teach vs, that, <hi>à iuvantibus et nocentibus,</hi> from ſuch things as helpe, and ſuch things as hurt, a moſt inuincible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is drawne, and concluded. Is it not a generall rule with all Phyſitions, to continue the vſe of thoſe things which haue manifeſtly releeued and profited the patient (if there be no neceſſarie exception) and to fly and for beare the vſe of thoſe which haue hurt, or done no good? Nature teacheth brute beaſts, to ſeeke ſhadowed and coole places, in the heat of ſommer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ſenſe findes eaſe and refreſhing by the ſhaddow, and hurt and annoyance by the parching ſunne. Apparant it is, that my Potable gold did euen miraculouſly refreſh, helpe, profite and comfort this diſeaſed gentleman, of whom this queſtion firſt grew. For his vnderſtanding was thereby recouered: quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, reſt, and ſleepe procured: naturall and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſweating cauſed: and the poyſon of his diſeaſe driuen from the center and heart, whereby the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtules and exitures did againe appeare and come forth. All arguments and ſignes of good eſtate and temper in that diſeaſe did appeare as portending a perfect recouerie. On the other ſide, whatſoeuer the Medicines adminiſtred by theſe two other Doctors were, before or after my comming, I know not. But, moſt certaine it is, that whatſoeuer they gaue, or howſoeuer they handled the matter, much hurt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, euen the greateſt miſchiefe that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to a languiſhing patient. For all the concourſe of his former grieuous, direfull, and mortall ſympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall accidents returnes with double ſtrength, when his heart and vital ſpirits were not able to reſiſt.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:280:39"/> The ſtriking in againe of the exitures, rauing, wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and (which only remained to conclude the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie) Death it ſelfe, the laſt of all lines that man can draw: and a true line to draw and direct vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding men to the true cauſe of his death. Theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances compulſarily wrung from me, be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the euidence of this verity to all men, that will not maliciouſly ſpurne againſt apparant truth. But my traducers doe ſtill ſpiderlike ſucke poyſon in ſtead of hony, and force themſelues to an vnnaturall vomit of theſe humors againſt this medicine, truly of gold, and truly potable. In which bitterneſſe if they did not ſtill perſiſt, againſt their owne ſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, regard of vertue and veritie, wounding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny honeſt hearts, with falſe ſuggeſtions againſt my good name, and the innocuous worthineſſe of this Medicine, and defrauding many poore languiſhing ſoules of the vſe and benefite thereof, I would, and ſurely gladly would, for their ſakes, haue forborne the narration and report of this true ſtorie: Which I am by them compelled to publiſh for my Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MIſtres Cicely Boulſtred, a worthie gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">Extreme vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting.</note> and virgine, attending in neere ſeruice our gracious Queene, in good fauour and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, fell ſicke, and had greiuous paſſions. Vnto whome diuers of the moſt famous Phyſitions of the Colledge were called. Who with great care, and their vtmoſt skill, ſparing no coſt (as was fitting in ſuch a place) adminiſtred all kinds of conducing Medicines, both Cordials, and other reſpectiuely to the cauſe of her diſeaſe, and paſſions: both ſuch as be ready in the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:280:39"/> ſhoppes, as others by ſome ſingularitie of Art prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Her paſſions ſtill continued, if not encreaſed. Continuall vomiting, and reiection of whatſoeuer ſhe tooke, meate, drink, medicines: with ſwoundings, torture, torments of euery part of her body. A miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and pitifull ſpectacle, much lamented of many very honourable perſons. Shee could not reſt nor ſleepe night nor day. So that ſinking vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of this affliction, with the violence and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof, her ſtrength vtterly failed. Shee could not retaine ſo much as one drop of any broth or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nouriſhment. Her Stomacke by coniecture of all Phyſitions, was drawen together and ſhut vp, without any power or faculty to performe the offices of nature. In this miſerable eſtate, this diſtreſſed gentlewoman languiſhed two whole monthes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any eaſe or releefe by the vſe of any the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines giuen her by the aduiſe of the ſaid Phyſitions: all things tending to a more deſperate and Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicable eſtate. Whereupon the mother of this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman demanded of theſe ſaid Doctors, whether they had any hope to giue helpe, or at leaſt wiſe eaſe to her daughter; elſe ſhe ſaid ſhe would ſend for <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Anthony.</hi> Thoſe Doctors hereupon limited them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to a certaine time, which they ſpent in their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt habilities to perform, to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I ſhold not be called. To which purpoſe they commanded an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary to attend in the Chamber of the patient all the next day and night, and euery third houre to giue her a Cordiall. Then voluntarily they ſaid to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Send for <hi>Doct. Anthony</hi> if you will, and God ſend him good ſucceſſe with your daughter. Then was I ſent for, and finding this gentlewoman in ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate a caſe, left and giuen ouer by all the Doctors of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:280:40"/> the Colledge as not to be recouered, (for beſides the aduiſe of theſe Six, there had beene publike conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Colledge, as is requiſite in ſuch like caſes which ſildome come in vſe) I deſired God to bleſſe my endeauours, and to continue his bleſſings in the adminiſtration of this my happy medicine. After a ſmall time, vpon due and mature conſideration of all things, I gaue her at the firſt, not a whole ſpoonfull of my <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> as in other caſes, but much leſſe, ſcarce a quarter ſo much; which ſhe caſt vp againe with a vehement force and torture of her body. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while after I gaue her as much more, which ſhe caſt vp in the ſame manner as ſhe did the firſt. Againe I gaue it the third time, ſome part of which ſhee alſo caſt vp, but kept ſome, with a kind of ſtrife or conflict betweene the medicine and the maladie. Then I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, that ſhe ſhould not further be troubled for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but to try if ſhee could now take a little reſt or ſleepe: So ſhe diſpoſed her ſelfe thereunto, and ſlept ſoundly a whole houre; which diuers of great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then preſent can witneſſe. For ſhe ſnored that we all heard: Which ſeemed ſtrange to all: conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for a long time before ſhee had taken no reſt. When ſhe waked, ſhe ſaid that ſhe found her ſelfe ſomewhat better at eaſe. Then (which was the fourth time) I gaue her halfe a ſpoonful, which ſhe kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any contending or trouble to her body. This gaue me, and many worthy gentlewomen there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, great hope of a good recouerie. Wherein (God be praiſed) we were not deceiued. For in all the other adminiſtring of this Medicine, orderly, as ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare, increaſing the quantitie, her ſpirits were releeued, ſhe daily recouered ſtrength, all the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſymptomes and accidents of her diſeaſes ceaſed,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:280:40"/> her ſickneſſe fully left her, and ſhe recouered perfect health. Thus with the vſe of this happy Medicine, this gentlewoman was recouered, and cured of that dangerous diſeaſe, wherein thoſe other Doctors had wearied themſelues, and forſaken her; at which her friends wondred, mine reioyced, and other malicious aduerſaries fretted: for which God be praiſed. If they will call theſe the effects of Iugling, and of a corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue Medicine, they will hardly finde any Cordiall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all their Diſpenſatories and Magiſtrall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions. The cauſe and effect are Eſſentiall Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe Lady and wife of <hi>Sir Francis Leake</hi> Knight,<note place="margin">Continuall vomiting and deſtillation of Reume conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing many moneths.</note> being now conceiued of her firſt childe, was fallen into many infirmities. Shee had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall and abundant ſlux at her mouth, cauſed by collection of phlegmaticke and pituitous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: Alſo a continuall vomiting and caſting, euer after any food taken. Her flux ceaſed not neither day nor night. She was brought to that weaknes &amp; lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in her body, that al her friends thought ſhe was in a conſumption. During the time of this ſicknes (which was fiue moneths) ſhe vſed many medicines in hope of remedy, but found none. And therefore iuſtly feared eyther miſcarying her trauell, or the loſſe of her owne life. Whereupon, by the perſwaſion of ſome friends, which knew right well the efficacie of my Potable gold, ſhe tooke therof the third month before the time of her deliuery, and at ſeuerall times continued the vſe of it. By which meanes, her vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp; flux of ſpitting ceaſed, ſhe recouered ſtrength
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:280:41"/> and good habit: and all the reſt of the time of her childe bearing, continued in very good health and diſpoſition. And in due time was deliuered of a faire and ſtrong Sonne, which is yet liuing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe Lady and wife of <hi>Sir Edward Barret</hi> knight,<note place="margin">Perill in childbirth.</note> and ſiſter to the forenamed Lady, being in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of childbirth, in ſuch hazard and extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of hard labour, that both her Midwiues &amp; all other there preſent deſpaired both of ſafety and life of mother and child; by counſell of a great Ladie then in my chamber tooke of my Potable gold, and beyond the expectation of them all, was preſently deliuered of a child in good liking But the after burden ſtayed, which in that weakeneſſe made them feare the like danger. Therefore they gaue her the ſame Medicine againe, by which the after burden fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, ſhe recouered, and did well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>THis Medicine hath likewiſe bin happy and ſucceſfull to very many others, Weomen in like caſes, euen after the childe hath beene dead in their bodies, and they giuen ouer in their laſt extremities. So that it is ſcarſe poſſible to finde any Medicine to match this in ſuch caſes, whereof I will ſet downe a few examples.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Ioſeph Pemberton</hi> Haberdaſher of Ipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich<note place="margin">Childbirth.</note> in the Countie of Suffolke, was deliuered by meanes of this Potable gold, being in great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and danger, by reaſon of her hard labour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:280:41"/>
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Oratio Paluaſino,</hi> was recouered<note place="margin">Childbirth.</note> by the ſame Medicine, beeing in great danger through hard labour in childe-birth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>IN like manner was the wife of <hi>Thomas Blackeborne</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Childbirth.</note> Citizen of London, when ſhe had beene two daies in labour, ſafely deliuered by this helpe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Nicholas Colman</hi> in Great Saint Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholmewes,<note place="margin">Childbirth.</note> was euen at the point of Death, and vpon the taking of this <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> was preſently deliuered, and her life preſerued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAſter Foxton</hi> in Red Croſſe ſtreete, had his wife<note place="margin">Dead birth.</note> in the like caſe, and in greater danger, by reaſon of the childe in her body being dead.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe like <hi>Foetus mortuus,</hi> or dead birth, the wife of<note place="margin">Dead birth.</note> 
                     <hi>Maſter Caſtle,</hi> of Hatfield Peuerell in Eſſex, had carried in her body three daies, neither could ſhe be deliuered by any helpe, vntill ſhee tooke the <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:280:42"/>
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Harde</hi> dwelling vpon <hi>Saint Peters</hi> Hill in London, was deliuered of a dead<note place="margin">Dead birth.</note> childe, yet neuertheleſſe ſhe was ſtill full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable paines. Whereupon the wife of <hi>M. Fitzgarret</hi> Eſquire neere dwelling, gaue vnto her of my <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> the next day after her deliuery of that childe, at 9. of the clocke in the morning. And the ſame day at 2. of the clocke in the after noone, ſhee was deliuered of an other dead childe, and then preſently recouered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſt. Iohn Bingle</hi> of the Exchequer was<note place="margin">Perill of Childbirth.</note> in her trauell in great peril of death, vnto whom a graue gentlewoman there preſent at her labour, gaue of my <hi>Aurum Potabile;</hi> with which helpe, both ſhee and the childe were ſaued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe Lady and wife of <hi>Sir Iohn Pretiman</hi> knight,<note place="margin">Burning feuer in Childbirth.</note> being in childe-bed, fell into a burning feuer: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhe could take no reſt nor ſleepe: And other very violent paſſions ſhe endured. She was not willing to take any manner of Medicine. Only <hi>Aurum Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile</hi> ſhee tooke, and was quickly reſtored to health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſt. Edmund Kingſtone,</hi> of Gloceſter<note place="margin">Burning feuer and bloody flux in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</note> ſhire, being in childe-bed had a burning feuer, and with it a bloody flux. She was throughly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſame meanes which the <hi>Lady Pretiman</hi> vſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:280:42"/>
                  <p>AN other gentlewoman of the ſame Countie,<note place="margin">Feuer and ſcouring in Childbed.</note> the wife of <hi>Chriſtopher Blackewell,</hi> was by the ſame meanes cured of a feuer, with an exceſſiue ſcouring, lying in childbed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Iohn Sherington</hi> of London<note place="margin">Preſeruation of Aborte.</note> Marchant, being with childe, had many paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and euident cauſes, to make her feare abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or miſcarrying. Beeing therefore aduiſed thereunto, ſhe tooke of my <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> daily a proportionable quantitie, and went out her full time, receiued Gods bleſſing in the ſafe deliuery of a faire childe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notice">
                  <p>Whereby it appeareth that this Medicine hath diuers vertues and faculties: As in caſe, both to promote the birth where it is ſtayed, be the birth aliue or dead: as alſo to ſtay and preuent abortion of miſcarrying, vnto the full time and periode of the naturall birth, which in the power of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is but one: That is, the onely comforting, ſtrenghtning, and enabling of nature, to promote and performe her owne actions, which way ſoeuer is moſt fit for the ſafety &amp; health of the body, as in other caſes before hath beene obſerued. And not only profitable to each mother in all thoſe former cauſes, but to the infant alſo, as ſhall appeare by one Relation, which here followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:280:43"/>
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Richard Browne</hi> Eſquire,<note place="margin">Perill in Childbirth.</note> dwelling in the Blacke fryers, was long in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of childbirth, and in great danger, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſhe had two midwiues with her. A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine gentlewoman and neighbour being then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, perſwaded to ſend for ſome of my <hi>Aurum Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile,</hi> and to giue it her. One Midwife ſaid, ſhe had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meanes to giue her. But when all meanes fayled, and ſmall hope of life remained, then was my <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> ſent for. And after it was twice adminiſtred vnto her, ſhe was ſafe deliuered of a liuing and well liking childe, God be praiſed. The next day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">The new borne Infant in danger.</note> the ſame gentlewoman and neighbour, came to viſite the mother and childe, finding the childe in the Midwiues lap, not well, but languiſhing and ill. The Midwife deſired of this gentlewoman ſome of the <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> for to giue the childe. It was then asked, whether ſhe, who had denied it vnto the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the former day, would now giue it vnto ſo yong an infant? The Midwife anſwered, that hauing ſeene the admirable effect thereof the day before, ſhe doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not of ſucceſſe in the childe. She gaue it therefore vnto the childe, mixed with breaſtmilke, and the childe preſently amended.</p>
                  <div type="notice">
                     <p>If therefore ſuch yong infants, which skantly haue ſeene the light of the Sun, and haue brought from the mothers wombe their infirmities, and not taken them by miſdiet or miſorder, doe finde releefe by this Medicine; as alſo women in their concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in time of their deliuerie, and afterwards lying in childbed, as is euidently ſet downe in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:280:43"/> particularitie: Euen in this only caſe, it meriteth that account, that no Lady or gentlewoman of accompt, ſhould at any time bee vnfurniſhed thereof, for the benefit of themſelues, and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, in caſe of neceſſitie: ſeeing that no Medicine is more powerfull, more ſecure, more pleaſing to take.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>SIr <hi>Lewis Lewknar</hi> knight, in the yeare of our Lord 1611, fell dangerouſly ſicke with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<note place="margin">The Plague or Peſtilence.</note> feuer, &amp; vehement paſſions. He ſent for two famous Phyſitions of the Citie of London; which followed and plyed him ſixe daies with al the condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible remedies they could deuiſe, but without any ſucceſſe. For they neither eaſed his paſſions, nor aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the burning heate and furie of the feuer: So that the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euery day waxed worſe &amp; worſe: at the laſt, an Apoſteme appeared in his groyne, a true token in ſuch a diſeaſe, of a peſtilent and contagious infection: which at that time, though not ſince, was very hot in London. Thereupon theſe Doctors excuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in that they were tied to the attendance of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe noble perſons, whom they were loth to infect. And therefore, were compelled to bid him farewell. And accordingly left this worthy gentleman, to wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with this diſeaſe, for the cure of which they were waged, and by conſcience thereunto tyed; and his truſt in them was repoſed. They hauing thus taken their leaues, I was ſent for, not knowing the diſeaſe, which could not long hide it ſelfe, hauing ſuch mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt tokens. Yet I thought it, againſt both charity and honeſtie, now being with him, to forſake him. And therefore reſolued (by the grace of God) with ſome
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:280:44"/> powerfull and ſtrong Antidote, to expell the poyſon from his heart, and afterwards to proceede for his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recouery, as occaſion ſhould be miniſtred. To which purpoſe, I firſt gaue him ſixe graines of my Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of gold, mixed appropriatly. After which, in a ſmall time, he began to ſweate, which continued all that night, and a great part of the next day. The next night, and ſo euery day for 4. daies more, I gaue againe the ſame Medicine, in the ſame quantity, which cauſed abundant ſweating, whereby both the malignitie of the feuer and the vnnaturall heate was exceedingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated: the Apoſteme, which was riſen very great, did daily decreaſe, and at laſt quite vaniſhed, only with a certaine ſticticke plaſter outwardly applied. Thus he was cured of this mortall and contagious diſeaſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was knowne abroad of what he was ſicke: which I would not now haue publiſhed, but that the Knight himſelfe, hath not beene ſparing amongſt his friends to report both what his ſickneſſe was, and the ſtory of his Phyſitions and recouery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe yeare before, I had likewiſe cured of the ſame<note place="margin">The Plague or Peſtilence.</note> diſeaſe, with an Apoſteme alſo appearing, the Lady and wife of the ſame worthy knight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe Lady <hi>Edmonds</hi> widdow, about the age of 78.<note place="margin">Dropſie and Iaundiſe in extreame old age.</note> yeares, a Lady well knowne in Court: (ſo likewiſe are thoſe that formerly are named) about three yeeres paſt was fallen into a dropſie, with all the ſymptomes thereunto belonging. Her belly, face, legs, hands,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:280:44"/> greatly ſwelled: blood waſted and ſpent: not free from the Iaundiſe, nor far from a Conſumption. How dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous her caſe was, is ſufficiently knowne. She was perfectly reſtored (praiſed be God) in ſhort time, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being miniſtred vnto her, but only the <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> and Eſſence of Gold. This Lady, ſpared not either for coſt, or due obſeruation to preſerue life and health, after that ſhe had once found comfort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; for during the ſpace of 12. daies at the firſt, ſhee tooke euery morning 3. graines of the Eſſence, diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in a ſpoonfull of <hi>Aurum potabile:</hi> and the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion was taken at night when ſhe went to reſt. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo before dinner and ſupper, at each time one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> alone. After 12. daies were ſpent, and that her ſtomacke was amended, naturall reſt returned, her ſtrength increaſed, the diſeaſe aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and all the ſtate of her body bettered, then the Lady tooke of the Eſſence but once a day. And ſo by degrees all things in leſſer proportion. Needfull it was, that this Lady ſhould take theſe helpes in greater proportion, then vſuall, partly in regard of the Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, being a capitall diſeaſe: partly alſo in regard of her yeeres, in which nature was not ſo powerfull to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome the malady, as in youth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>SIr <hi>Thomas Parrey</hi> knight, Chancelor of the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and of his Maieſties priuy Councell, being<note place="margin">Extreme cough in age and want of ſleepe.</note> of the age of 77. yeares, this laſt winter was much deiected in habilitie and ſtrength of body eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry waies. His appetite abated, his ſleepe diminiſhed, tormented with an extreame cough day and night, not able in many weekes together, to goe forth of his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:280:45"/> houſe for execution of his place. He had vſed good helpes of learned Phyſitions, from time to time all the winter long. In February laſt I was brought vnto this honourable perſon; and finding that the beſt Medicines ordinarily, in vſe had nothing auailed, I perſwaded him to take of my <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he willingly condeſcended. I gaue him thereof in the morning in bed faſting, as alſo one houre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dinner and Supper, at each time a ſpoonfull. Alſo whereas vſually his ſleepe was but two houres euery night, which was after he was firſt laid in bed, and then afterwards being once awaked, he ſlept no more all that night, but continually did lie coughing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he aroſe in the morning: my counſell was, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his firſt ſleepe, his Honor ſhould take two graines of the Eſſence of golde, diſſolued in one ſpoonfull of the <hi>Aurum Potabile:</hi> which doing, he alwaies within halfe an houre, was at good and quiet reſt, his Cough ceaſed, and he ſlept quietly vntill ſixe of the clocke in the morning. This courſe it pleaſed him to continue vntill the 12. of Aprill, in which time he daily gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtrength and habilitie of body to vndergoe any ſeruice of his Maieſtie. And thus he continueth ſtill to the praiſe of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Certaine yong gentleman, onely Sonne and<note place="margin">Debilitie of retention of ſperme.</note> heire vnto his Father being of great poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, complained vnto me that his ſperme paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from him vnſenſibly both day and night, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his body was much enfeebled, his complexion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and a Conſumption imminent. A marriage was tendered vnto this yong gentleman, being an heire alſo. Conditions agreed vpon by Parents on both
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:280:45"/> ſides, both for Dowre and Ioynter. The father of this gentleman being in feare of his ſonnes life, was loath to make any perfect Contract, vntill he had found Remedie for his ſonne. Hee vſed the beſt helpe that the Country could afforde, wherein he liued. But finding none, he brought vp his ſonne to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, vſed my counſell; and with the helpe of <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> the Eſſence of Golde, and a Solution of Pearle which in ſuch caſe I doe vſe, he hath recouered perfect ſtate of body, is married, and hath Iſſue. This Gentleman about twelue Moneths ſince being in London, came to viſite me, whome when I beheld I knew not vntill he had manifeſted himſelfe vnto me; ſo greatly was his body altered euen into a full vigor and perfect conſtitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Robert Dixon,</hi> Secretary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Sir Henry Montague</hi> Knight, Recorder of the<note place="margin">Speech and ſence loſt in Childbed.</note> Citie of London, being deliuered in childbed; was poſſeſſed with a moſt violent burning fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Shee had three Phyſitions of great woorth, who miniſtred vnto her ſuch helpes, as Art could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foard in that caſe. Not preuailing, they left her being ſenſeleſſe. Then did the <hi>Lady Tanfield</hi> ſend vnto me for ſome of my <hi>Auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Potabile,</hi> which her <hi>Ladiſh.</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be giuen vnto this gentlewoman. In ſhort time after ſheefell into a ſweate, not long after ſhee ſlept; and when ſhee did awake, ſhee had recouered both ſence and ſpeech, her burning feuer was aſſwaged, and in few daies after by Iudgement of al her friends, ſhee ſeemed paſt all perill and danger of life. But ſhortly after, riſing vp out of her bed, and ſitting vp o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer long, ſhee tooke cold, ſo that all the parts of her
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:280:46"/> body became colde &amp; were vtterly benummed, and without ſenſe, her ſpeech failed, &amp; her ſtrength &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits much abated. The former worthy <hi>Lady</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed therof, did ſend againe of my <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> vnto her, which inſtantly put her into a ſweat, after ſhe was in bed, and by degrees reſtored her vnto perfect health. The ſame gentlewoman being lately deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of two daughters, fell into the like paſſions both of heate and colde, and in each of theſe extremities was releeued with the Eſſence of Gold, as formerly ſhe had beene, with <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>William Rowden</hi> the Kings Maieſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant<note place="margin">Speech and ſence loſt.</note> and Marſhall of his Hall, 70. yeares of age, or thereabout, with a continuall Ardent feuer which held him long, he was at the laſt brought to that debilitie and weakeneſſe, that he altogether kept his bed, tooke no reſt day nor night, but for the moſt part lay ſenſeleſſe, not knowing what was ſaid or done vnto him. In this extremitie I was brought, and it pleaſed God that by theſe former helpes, he was recouered, and remaineth ſtill in perfect health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>William Gore</hi> now Alderman &amp; Sheriffe<note place="margin">Aquartane A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue.</note> of the citie of London, threeſcore yeares of age or thereabout, dwelling in Bow lane, for the ſpace of many Moneths languiſhed of a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine feuer. In which time, by preſcript of learned Phyſitions, he had taken ſo many Medicines, that he vtterly abhorred all vſuall Phyſicke. When he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:280:46"/> by ſome of his well wiſhing friends, that my <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> was very Cordiall, effectuall in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not loathſome or vnpleaſing to take, he was reſolued to make vſe thereof, although he had reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued neuer to vſe any more Phyſicke. But being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by ſome of his Phyſitions, my profeſſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, he refrained the ſpace of ſome weekes, vntill meere neceſſitie (by reaſon of his ſtill continuing quartane, and his ſtrength daily abating) enforced him to ſend for me. I miniſtred vnto him at returne of his next fit, a ſmall quantitie of my <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> with 2. graines of the Eſſence of golde; which gaue him ſuch contentment during the time of his fit, that his feuer was much more tollerable then formerly it had beene, and himſelfe in farre better vigor after his fit. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did he much admire what reaſon his Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons could alleadge, for the diſabling of that Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. To conclude, in very few fittes, this Medicine cleared him of his feuer, it brought him to quiet reſt, reſtored him to appetite, and brought him to good habilitie and ſtrength of body. And vntill this time, it is and hath beene a continuall releefe vnto him, whenſoeuer hee findeth himſelfe inclining to any manner of debilitie or ſickneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>AS in this caſe, ſo haue they dealt with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the Nobility of this land &amp; honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonages, who in extremity of their ſickeneſſe, hauing firſt vſed (and that fruitleſly) all the courſe of Phyſicke which their Phyſitions in Art could aduiſe them) haue deſired the helpe of my Aurum Potabile. But haue beene diuerted by malicious cauillations of thoſe, who rather
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:280:47"/> deſire their owne lucre and gaine, then the life of their patients. Neuertheleſſe ſome of the right Honourable, not beeing daunted by their terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings (more fit for children and babes, then for men and women of vnderſtanding) haue made happie vſe thereof both in Court and Citie; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for cauſes conuenient, it is not publikely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulged, and yet peraduenture not vtterly ſilenced. But time, in his due time, will bring the truth to light.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Mathew Dale,</hi> Iuſtice of Peace &amp; Iudge in Gilde Hall, 76. yeares of age, hath ſundry times beene troubled with an infirmitie inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to age: that is, want of Retention of his vrine. Whereby ſometimes in the night ſeaſon, he hath bin inforced more then twenty times to make water: whereby his naturall reſt (which ſhould haue ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nature) was taken from him: and conſequently his ſtomacke failed, &amp; his ſtrength abated. Vpon the vſe of <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> theſe extremities were abated, and he continued vntill the end of his daies, in good ſtate of body, anſwerable vnto his yeeres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Mathew Dale,</hi> 70. yeares of<note place="margin">Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lungs.</note> age, hauing an infirmitie of the Lungs, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vncurable, was neuertheleſſe preſerued in good ſtate of body, many yeares with helpe of this <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:280:47"/>
                  <p>SIr <hi>William Hericke</hi> Knight, had by his Lady two<note place="margin">Falling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> daughters, the one after the other. Each of them being 20. weekes of age, was taken with the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſie or falling ſicknes, and died of that diſeaſe. After them, he had by his ſaid wife a third daughter; then did they change their Nurſe, ſuſpecting that ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect might be in the Nurſes milke. When this daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came to the age of 16. weeks, the Epileptical fits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to poſſeſſe this infant, and daily the fits increaſed, vntill the diſeaſe came to the height. Then was the Nurſe &amp; child ſent for hither to London; haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g heard that I had cured ſome in the like infirmity. The father vſed my help in this caſe. It pleaſed God that with the helpe of my <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> and Eſſence of gold (with ſome helpes giuen to the nurſe) I perfectly cured that Child of this dangerous infirmitie. This was done in the ſpring time. Then I aduiſed the Lady, that the like ſhould be done at next fall of the leafe: But that being neglected, the child vpon the feaſt day of All-Saints next following, fell into the ſame diſeaſe againe; which I likewiſe cured the ſecond time. Since this time, being now foure yeeres paſt, this child neuer had fit, praiſed be God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>IN like manner, and of the ſame infirmitie, a Sonne<note place="margin">Falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> of <hi>Sir George Wright</hi> Knight, being a yeare old was cured by me, and many others, whereof ſome ſhall be mentioned in this treatiſe hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>IOhn Vnet,</hi> belonging to the right honourable <hi>Sir</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Speech and ſenſe loſt</note> 
                     <hi>Henry Hubbard</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Juſtice of the Common-Pleas, 40. yeeres of age or thereabout, after long ſickneſſe, was at the laſt brought to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and weakneſſe, that he lay depriued of ſpeech
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:280:48"/> and ſenſe. The bell tolled for him: The ſeruants of the houſe had taken their leaue of him: no hope of life remained. Being in this manner at point of death, ſome of my <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> was put into his mouth: by which he was brought againe to ſpeech, to ſenſe, and laſtly reſtored to perfect health, being formerly by iudgment of all, ordained for death. Of this caſe, <hi>Raymund Lully</hi> in his booke of the Quinteſſence wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in this manner. <hi>We terme them dead men, not thoſe which abſolutely are dead, but thoſe of whom by the opinion of Phyſitions there is vtter deſpaire, ſo that they are forſaken by all Phyſitions, and the actions of life haue relinquiſhed them, and be depriued of ſenſe. If ſuch like men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>reputed thus dead men, ſhall recouer life and health by a Quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, then may they iuſtly be ſaid to be reuiued from death.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>IN like manner was there an other, whoſe name is<note place="margin">Speech and ſence loſt</note> 
                     <hi>Robert Brodbottome,</hi> a Citizen, 60. yeares of age, neighbour vnto <hi>Sir Lewis Lewknar</hi> then dwelling in Alderſgate ſtreete; being likewiſe at deaths doore, the bell hauing tolled for him the ſpace of three houres. The ſaid Knight, when he vnderſtood that it tolled for his neighbour whom he well loued, ſent him of my <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> willing the wife of the ſaid patient by any poſſible meanes, to put the ſame into his mouth. Which being done, he ſhortly after fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſleepe, ſweating in his ſleepe, &amp; after his awaking, his ſenſe and ſpeech returned, and himſelfe recouered health, and yet is liuing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe daughter and heire of <hi>Sir Walter Coape</hi> knight, now Lady and wife of <hi>Sir Henry Rich</hi> knight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:280:48"/> then dangerouſly ſicke of the ſmall Pocks (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<note place="margin">Small poxe</note> many worthy Knights, Ladies, and gentlewomen haue miſcaried of late) was preſently releeued by vſe of my <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> and the ſmall Pocks expulſed plentifully.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>IN the ſmall Pocks alſo, and likewiſe in the meaſels, diuers haue beene recouered, whoſe only names I record, and none haue miſcaried to my knowledge which in due time haue embraced the benefite of this medicine.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Lady and wife of Sir Richard Ogle knight.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A gentle woman belonging to the Lady and wife of Sir Edward Barret knight.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sir Henry Caries Page.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sir Henry Caries daughter, of the meaſels.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Sonne and heire of Sir Henry Cary, of the ſmall pox.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A young daughter of Sir Richard Norton knight, of the Meaſels, which were ſtriken in and recoiled by cold taking whereby the child was in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Kinſwoman of Miſtris Browne of Eſſex, wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Seruant of Maſter Marſh Eſquire, then dwelling in Colman-ſtreete.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Maid ſeruant, belonging to Ro. Dixon before mentioned.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>An other maid ſeruant of Maſter Iohn Morris Marchant, dwelling neere vnto leaden hall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>An Infant of Mr. Price the Kings ſeruant.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:280:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAily experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alſo hath taught vs of late, that very many both young and old haue miſcaried of the Small Pox, euen vnder the hands of the beſt practiſed Phyſitions, although the cure of them be accounted no difficult matter: vnto whom, if this approued Medicine, ſo ſecure from danger: ſo powerfull in corroborating the Heart, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the venemous malignitie of that Diſeaſe, had beene at hand, and had beene adminiſtred in due time and forme, no doubt but (the vertue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſiue being fortified in the patient, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall venenoſitie ſubtiliated) if not all, yet ſome of them, might by this only Medicine haue beene recouered. As the vſe hereof hath preuented death in many, ſo likewiſe very many wanting the benefit thereof, in the flowre of their age periſhed; which haue vſed purgatiue Medicines, whoſe propertie is to draw malignant humors from the externall parts, vnto the center of the body, and to the very Heart it ſelfe. I leaue this matter to bee conſidered of, by thoſe whom in like caſe it may concerne hereafter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe Honorable <hi>Lady</hi> and widdow <hi>Doretie Skot,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vomiting of ſuſtenance in old age.</note> ſometime the wife of <hi>Sir Thomas Skot</hi> Knight of the age of 78. yeares, for the ſpace of many daies could retaine no manner of ſuſtenance, but inſtantly caſt vp by vomit whatſoeuer ſhee receiued. Neither could this be ſtayed by any Medicine miniſtred
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:280:49"/> vnto her. All meanes failing, my <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this extremitie. And after taking thereof, ſhee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tooke any manner of other ſuſtenance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſame. Hereby it may appeare, that this one and the ſame Medicine, doth ſometime procure vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, when nature would be vnburdened, and at other times it ſuppreſſeth vomit, when nature is ſo infee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that it would faine retaine nutriment for ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but cannot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAſter Napper</hi> Eſquire, dwelling in Oxford, 60. yeares of age, was long time perplexed with a<note place="margin">Vomiting and ſcooring.</note> very ſtrange infirmity. He was diuers times taken with an extreme vomiting, with a ſcooring likewiſe, which both continued the ſpace of 2. or 3. daies commonly euery houre without intermiſſion vntill his body was vtterly exhauſted. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he became ſo feeble and weake, that he was inforced to keepe his bed many daies, vntill by degrees he recouered ſome ſtrength againe. But when his body began to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate, then did he fall into his former paſſions. In this manner he continued one whole yeare more. He vſed for Remedie, the counſell and aduiſe of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions both at Oxford and London. When all their meanes auailed not, then did he ſend vnto me for my <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> which by the helpe of God preuailed in this caſe, to the great admiration of many.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter William Wiſeman</hi> Counſellor at the Law, after her ſafe deliuery in Childbirth, was poſſeſſed both with a feuer, as alſo with an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:280:50"/> and a dangerous flux, <hi>tam per Menſtrua quàm per ſedes.</hi> Her ſleepe alſo was thereby vtterly taken from her. By meanes whereof ſhee was brought vnto great Imbecillitie and deſpaire of life. In this dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous caſe, after the fruitleſſe helpe of other Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhe was recouered and perfectly reſtored, with the Eſſence of my golde in few daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>SIr Edward Barret</hi> Knight, hauing his abode<note place="margin">Eſſex Ague.</note> ſometime in Eſſex neere vnto the Mariſhes (a Country much ſubiect to Agues) was two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times poſſeſſed with that kinde of feuer. And each time he was freed from that feuer, by the onely helpe of my <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi> Many alſo of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, more then ten at one ſeuerall time, haue beene taken with that Country feuer. One eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, a woman, hauing chiefe gouernment ouer the family, was ſo grieuouſly afflicted therewith, that her ſenſes were taken from her, and other ſuch like accidents ſo oppreſſed her, that there remained ſmall hope of life. Yet it pleaſed God, that both ſhee and the reſt, in ſhort time were recouered (although the Agues of thoſe parts doe commonly continue long:) as alſo in one part of Kent, where many haue beene releeued by my <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> after that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes haue failed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAſter Doctor Sauage, Doctor</hi> of the Ciuill Lawes,<note place="margin">Eſſex Ague.</note> 56. yeares of age, lying ſicke in Eſſex of the like feuer, ſent for me to come downe vnto him. Beeing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:280:50"/> now with him, and before I adminiſtred any thing vnto him, hee was ſtrangely taken with convulſions and Crampes, in his hands, feete, legges, face and in all the exterior parts of his body, with extreme tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, lamentable to beholde. I appeaſed all theſe ſymptomes within the ſpace of one halfe houre, with the Eſſence of my gold, which in ſhort time brought him into a Sweat, and his Convulſions and Crampes ceaſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> feuer alſo was cured in very ſhort time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe ſame <hi>Doctor Sauage</hi> now lately within theſe two moneths, was taken with a malignant fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, a Diſeaſe now common in ſundry places. He was perfectly cured thereof, only with the Eſſence of golde. I gaue him thereof three graines, before the beginning of his fit, diſſolued in fiue ſpoonfuls of Endiue water with a little ſugar: and the like quantitie in the middeſt of his hot fit. This I did reiterate euery fit vntill the fourth fit. In which time he was free from his ague. But afterwards he fell into the like feuer againe, as alſo into thoſe former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, which could not by any helpe of Medicine be aſſwaged, vntill he was inforced to ſend vnto me, 17. miles for the Eſſence of golde: which being taken gaue him preſent releefe, admirable vnto them who were eye witneſſes of the effect thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Thomas Drywood</hi> of Northokenden in<note place="margin">Long langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon obſtructions.</note> the County of Eſſex, 30. yeeres of age, by reaſon of obſtructions and other inward cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, languiſhed a long time, became very leane, and ſo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:280:51"/> into a conſumption. Being therewith almoſt ſpent, my <hi>Aurum potabile</hi> was preſent remedy to him, and he liueth now in good health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Drywood,</hi> by the ſame<note place="margin">Weakneſſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter childbirth.</note> medicine recouered from a great weakneſſe and decaied eſtate, cauſed by hard labour in childbirth, and ſickneſſe afterwards.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Daughter of theirs being about 4. yeeres old,<note place="margin">Obſtruct.</note> hauing pined, and decaied long time of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne diſeaſe, vpon the taking of my Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gold, vomited vp a great quantity of viſcous tough matter, and then recouered preſently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Young daughter of <hi>Iohn Fanne</hi> Citizen, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note place="margin">Obſtruct.</note> in Alderſgate ſtreete, being fiue yeeres old, by reaſon of obſtructions in her liuer, ſplene, and breſt, which had long continued, and was thereby much hindred in her breathing, tooke one ounce only of my potable gold, after which ſhe caſt vp much ſlimy ſtuffe, tough, like molten glaſſe, that one could ſcarcely cut with a knife, and preſently ſhe amended, and ſhortly after became perfectly well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>William Snelling</hi> Fiſhmonger, dwelling in<note place="margin">Falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Thameſtreete, had a young infant of a yeere old, who was grieuouſly perplexed with the falling ſicknes. His fits were frequent and oft,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:280:51"/> ſometimes 20. in one day. So that the parents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought God, to take him to his mercy. out of that ſo great miſery: When diuers medicines had beene tried in vaine, he was at the laſt recouered by my Eſſence of gold, and neuer ſince was troubled with any fit, being more then 3. yeeres paſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Maid ſeruant of the Lady and wife of <hi>Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Convulſions.</note> 
                     <hi>Smith</hi> knight, being 22. yeeres old, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with moſt violent convulſions, and fits like vnto the falling ſickneſſe inceſſantly day and night for a long ſeaſon: not finding any eaſe by gliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and many other medicines giuen her by other Phyſitions. At laſt ſhe was by me cured of that feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſeaſe by this my Medicine, and neuer felt it ſince; three yeeres being paſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>AN Infant of a yeere and halfe old, daughter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Inward tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and gripings of an infant.</note> 
                     <hi>Sir Edward Barret</hi> knight, was long grieued with ſome inward torments and gripings in her belly. The Lady <hi>Paget,</hi> Baroneſſe, her grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, gaue her of my Potable Gold, with which ſhe preſently caſt vp ſome rawe fleagmaticke matter or humor, and was well for the ſpace of 2. houres: after which time ſhe complained as before, and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture worſe. The Lady her grandmother gaue her an other ſpoonfull, after which ſhe caſt againe much viſcous matter diuerſly coloured, and then ſlept a whole houre. But waking ſodenly, ſhe ſeemed as one ready to diepreſently, hauing many dangerous ſignes as ſowundings, and falling of her iawes &amp;c. So that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:280:52"/> the good Lady, holding this Infant all that while in her lap, was faine forcibly to open her mouth, and poured in an other ſpoonfull mixed with beere or ale. After which ſhe caſt againe a blackiſh and ill ſauoured ſlimy thicke ſtuffe. Then ſhe was well and recouered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Thomas Allin</hi> Eſquire, more then 60.<note place="margin">Extreame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</note> yeeres of age, being lodged in Broad ſtreete, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing then languiſhed a long time: at laſt being neere ſpent, he ſent for me: and with my Potable Gold eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſome other dietary meanes being alſo preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, he was perfectly reſtored in few daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Small,</hi> gentleman, an Attourney at the<note place="margin">A quartane ague.</note> law, and ſtudent of Furniualls Inne, 32. yeeres old, had lien ſicke of a quartane feuer many moneths, and had alſo the iaundiſe. He finding no helpe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther medicines, was in ſhort time perfectly cured by my <hi>Aurum potabile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>MAſter <hi>Thomas Tutteſhame</hi> gentleman, aged 20.<note place="margin">A quartane ague.</note> yeeres, ſonne of Maſter <hi>Anthony Tutteſhame,</hi> both of Staple Inne, was likewiſe cured of a quartane ague, by my potable gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Yong ſon of <hi>Sir Io. Taleſburrough</hi> knight, about<note place="margin">Eſſex ague.</note> 4. yeeres old, lay dangerouſly ſicke in Eſſex, of the popular and vniuerſarie diſeaſe, ordinarie in thoſe mariſh countries, and could not endure to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:280:52"/> take any medicines. He tooke my Eſſence of gold, with the <hi>aurum potabile</hi> at ſeuerall times, and was thereby perfectly cured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe daughter of <hi>Sir Anthony Capell</hi> knight, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout<note place="margin">A Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 14. yeares old, after a long ſickneſſe fell into a Conſumption, with extreme weakneſſe. Her father ſent vnto me for ſome of my pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble golde, whereiwth ſhee was in reaſonable time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly recouered, and reſtored to her former health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>FRancis Wonnam</hi> of Darkin in the Countie of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey,<note place="margin">Palſey of all the body.</note> Yeoman, was taken with a dead Palſey in all parts of his body. To whom <hi>Maſter William Rad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> Eſquire of the ſame Towne, gaue ſome of my potable golde which hee had in ſtore for his owne vſe, beeing oft times troubled with the Stone; by which meanes the ſaid <hi>Wonnam</hi> recouered, and had perfect vſe both of legs and hands.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Yong gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Io. Studolph,</hi> 17. yeares old, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Speech loſt, and vomiting,</note> then with his mother (a widdow) dwelling neere the foreſaid Darkin, was taken with a Palſey in his tongue; his ſpeech was taken from him, and whatſoeuer he did either eate or drinke, he caſt it vp. I was ſent for, and ſtaied there ſome three dayes. In which time, by intermiſſiue adminiſtring of my <hi>Aurum potabile,</hi> and Eſſence of gold, his vomiting was ſtaied, his ſpeech recouered, and he perfectly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But I heard afterwards by ſome of his friends,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:280:53"/> that about a yeare after he fell againe into the ſame Diſeaſe, and died thereof before he could conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſend for any helpe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAſter Iohn Coles,</hi> called <hi>Captaine Coles,</hi> about 44. yeares old, had long time beene troubled<note place="margin">Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lungs.</note> with a dangerous Diſeaſe of the Lungs, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of breath, coughing and with it, ſpitting of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten matter, and ſeemed to bee in full Conſumption. He was perfectly cured with the continued vſe of my Potable golde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEnry Smith</hi> ſeruant to <hi>Sir Edward Barret</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Palſey.</note> Knight, loſt his ſpeech by a Palſey, and ſo ſome time. Afterwards he perfectly recouered his ſpeech againe, by helpe of my <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Seruant of <hi>Sir Thomas Smith</hi> Knight, hauing beene long troubled with a quartane Ague,<note place="margin">Quartane.</note> finding no helpe by other Medicines which had beene giuen vnto him, was cured with my Pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>A Daughter of <hi>Maſter Fitzgarret</hi> Eſquire, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon <hi>Saint Peters</hi> Hill, was infected with<note place="margin">Plague.</note> the Plague or Peſtilence, and cured by the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe of my Eſſence of golde, diſſolued in my <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> with <hi>Carduus</hi> Water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:280:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ELizabeth Elward,</hi> being allied vnto <hi>Edward Rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> retainer to the <hi>Lord Kneuet,</hi> was likewiſe infected with the Plague, and becauſe the ſame<note place="margin">Plague.</note> 
                     <hi>Edward Rugham</hi> was continually attendant in White Hall vnder the <hi>Lord Kneuet,</hi> the ſaid Lord therefore perſwaded him to vſe my <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> for his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, being then in <hi>Edward Rughams</hi> houſe; which he did, and by it recouered his kinſwoman.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>DIuers other were alſo cured of the Plague at the ſame time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A maide ſeruant belonging to Maſter Iohn Morris, marchant, dwelling neere vnto Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Hall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A ſeruant of Sir Edward Conway Knight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maſt. Carre Counſellor at the Law, dwelling in Great Saint Bartholmewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A man ſeruant and a maide ſeruant in the houſe of Miſtris Randall widdow, dwelling on Saint Peters Hill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Three ſeruants in the houſe of Sir William He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke Knight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Maſter Arthur Luſon, Citizen in Paternoſter Row.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſter Seabright</hi> of London, Eſquire,<note place="margin">Convulſions with loſſe of ſenſe.</note> being about 60. yeares old, was often taken with diuers and ſundry paſſions, as Convulſions, and para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyticall ſtupefactions of her ſenſe of feeling; And had
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:280:54"/> beene ſundry times releeued by my Potable gold. But to ouercome, &amp; vtterly to ſuppreſſe the great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of thoſe humors or matter, which cauſed theſe fits ſo often to returne, without being perfectly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I aduiſed her to take ſometimes of my Eſſence of gold. Which when ſhee had taken, ſhee caſt vp a great quantitie of Melancholicke blacke ſtuffe. Since which time, ſhe hath neuer beene troubled with any of thoſe paſſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAſter Iohn Sherington</hi> of London, Marchant, had a ſonne about three yeares old, long time<note place="margin">Obſtructions in a childe.</note> deiected and weake, and had receiued many Medicines againſt the wormes and other cauſes which were ſuſpected, but to no purpoſe (for he daily grew worſe and worſe.) At laſt therefore, hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my Potable golde a few daies, he caſt vp a great quantity of tough, thicke, and viſcous humors. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which (the matter of Obſtructions being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) he preſently recouered perfect health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>ALſo a yong daughter then borne to this <hi>Maſter</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A new borne Infant.</note> 
                     <hi>Sherington,</hi> being ſixe moneths old, fell dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſicke, and with the ſame Medicine was reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>THe wife of <hi>Maſt. Coles</hi> dwelling in Colmanſtreete<note place="margin">Plague.</note> (after the death of her ſaid husband, who died of the Plague) ſhee beeing then with childe, was alſo
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:280:54"/> infected. And fearing in that caſe all ſtrong Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, vſed only my Potable golde and the Eſſence, with vſe whereof by Gods grace ſhe recouered, &amp; her childe ſaued, of which ſhee was after ſafely deliuered. The husband which tooke other Medicines, not this, died. The wife which refuſed all other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and tooke only this, recouered; Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the increaſe of danger by her childbearing. Let the due conſideration of this one caſe, ſtop the mouth of malice it ſelfe, and informe the enuious to glorifie God, for his great and good gifts beſtowed vpon men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>EDmund Nuſum</hi> dwelling neere Charing-Croſſe, fell into a dangerous ſickneſſe and long time continued therein. In this his diſtreſſe he ſent for a learned Phyſition of London, well knowne: who vſed his beſt skill and endeauours, for recouery of this patient. But failing in his expectation, he tolde the patients wife, that ſhe muſt ſhortly be a widdow, A worthy gentleman, their neighbour, pitying this caſe, ſent his man to me in this ſicke mans behalfe. I came, and found the Apothecarie at the patients dore, newly come from him, which ſaluted me with theſe, or the like words: You come tooo late, there is no good to be done. To whome I anſwered, that though I could doe no good, yet I would do no hurt. So when I came to the patient, and could not finde any likely ſignes, nor hopes of life, I vndertooke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerning his recouery; neither promiſed ſo much as hope. Yet for a triall, I gaue him ſome of my potable golde, and continued that adminiſtration all
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:280:55"/> that night, once in three houres. It pleaſed God that hee recouered, to the great admiration of all men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>NOt long after, the only ſonne of the aforeſaid Apothecarie, (whoſe name was <hi>Nathan Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi>) 17. yeares of age, was likewiſe taken with a violent burning feuer. He had the aduice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell not onely of the ſaid Phyſition before ſpecified, but alſo of many other of the Colledge. But the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent grew worſe and worſe, and at length became ſpeechleſſe, and was as it were vpon the threſhold, to take death by the hand. The father then, though in deſpaire of his ſonne, yet hauing ſeene the former ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, came haſtily vnto me, in the Sermon time (being then the Sabbath day) imploring my aide for his ſonnes recouerie, if yet it were poſſible. His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints preuailed. I gaue his ſonne of theſe materials, iterated by degrees as the caſe required. God bleſſed the meanes, and he recouered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAſter William Parkinton</hi> gentleman, likewiſe, dwelling neere vnto Charing-Croſſe, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently well knowne, lay dangerouſly ſicke, vſing the aduice and helpe of the ſaid before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phyſition. He neglected no meanes of ordinary courſe preſcribed by Phyſicke. Neuertheleſſe the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient found ſmall releefe. For the Phyſition himſelfe accounted him a dead man. So likewiſe did his wife, and other his friends, In this forlorne eſtate, I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him. I only gaue him of the Eſſence of gold,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:280:55"/> and the <hi>Aurum Potabile.</hi> And that God, who doth wound and heale: who bringeth vs to the brinke of the graue, and raiſeth vs vp againe, by this meanes, as his reuealed ordinance, reſtored him againe vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="account">
                  <p>
                     <hi>BY theſe three laſt inſtances, all dwelling neere vnto one place, and almoſt at one time, one Phyſition being called vnto them all, and they all forſaken by him, as deplored: yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, they all beeing recouered, by the only helpe of this Aurum Potabile: we muſt of force acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame to bee an extraordinary bleſſing ſent from God, for releefe of thoſe, who haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed the benefit thereof. And let no man depraue this Medicine, in that it is adminiſtred ſo diuerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It ought rather to be had in greater price. The neerer vnto ſimplicitie, the neerer to veritie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, in vaine are many things vſed, when one thing preuaileth. As in all the courſe of our life this is true, ſo likewiſe in adminiſtring of Phyſicke. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Damaſcen ſaith: It were a wicked fact to vſe a compound Medicine, where a ſimple profiteth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:280:56"/>
               <head>CONCLVSION OF THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y theſe euidences, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold experience ſincerely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, partly taken and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tranſlated out of Latine letters, ſent from ſeuerall parts beyond the ſeas; partly in Engliſh verbally ſet downe, as they came to me; any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man, not ſeduced by vaine oppoſitions, nor willfully preiudicate, nor peruerſly malicious, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily iudge, that this medicine, my Potable gold, is the moſt wholeſome, ſafe, &amp; operatiue medicine, which at this day is knowne to be had in vſe: both for the cure of deſperate and hopeleſſe ſickneſſes, when all helpe of man is accounted vaine: And for the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull reſtoring of the decaied ſtrength, and langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing powers of the body, with a ſingular comforting of the heart: As alſo, for a Prophylacticke, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of health. Which ſo being, the greater is their ſinne, which contrary to Gods commandement, Chriſtian charitie, the loue of truth, their dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their neighbour, and peraduenture their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimony of their owne conſcience, haue ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulently and deſpitefully inueighed againſt the true and vncontrollable virtues and effects thereof: And
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:280:56"/> in their waſt papers of impreſſion, haue attempted to ſhew the power of malicious <hi>Rhetoricke,</hi> thereby to wrong that good, which they themſelues cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto. Whereby ſo farre as their habilitie and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibilitie could ſtretch, they haue notoriouſly iniured, not me only, but all ſorts, ranks, and degrees of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſubiect to the vnreſpectiue tyranny of ſickneſſe, which maketh no difference betweene the Cottage and Pallace, the King and the Peaſant. The wrong to me, is, that for my loue and truth, workes of charitie, good intentions towards all, and good deſerts of as many as haue made, or hereafter ſhall make vſe of the fruites of theſe my labours: they haue rewarded me, with that which is vnder my backbiters tongues, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for reuerence, reproch, for my good deeds, and ſlander, for a recompence. But the wrong done to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hath many branches, and ſearcheth to the ſeate of greateſt honour. For (though I dare not ſay that it ſhould haue beene otherwiſe, by the adminiſtring hereof (the length and number of all daies being in Gods hand) yet to ſhew their warme charitie againſt all things, not in their owne Apothekes, they would not ſuffer our late yong Prince, worthy of immortall memorie, to vſe this ſo famouſly and aboue all excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions approued medicine; notwithſtanding in the vſe of all other, they found not ſo much as any hope. In a deſperate caſe, and a prognoſticated life, all rules both of learning and charitie allow, yea and require the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of any meanes, not noted of ill ſuſpicion: Much more ſo publikely and manifoldly teſtified, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable good effects which it had wrought in diuers perſons. But that Rubricke (<hi>Propter dignitatem perſonae &amp;c.</hi>) Giue ordinary medicines to great perſós, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the honour of the Phyſition, that he hath done
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:280:57"/> no hurt, <hi>ſcilicet,</hi> though he did no good, is neither Prophylacticke nor Therapeuticke. We ſay in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: As good neuer a whit as neuer the better. And ſuch is their pious affection towards all others whom it may concerne, that whatſoeuer happen, none of them will make vſe of this my potable gold, (which though not properly, yet emphatically may be called a diuine Medicine: and certainly with more merit, then their <hi>Gratia Dei, Manus Chriſti, Benedicta Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camenta, Diuinum Medicamentum</hi>) though it would ſaue a thouſand liues. Eſteeming (as it ſeemeth) that good which is ſo done without the Seplaſiaſticke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, to be their diſhonor, and delinement. Let all be ſoberly vſed, but where greateſt need is, the beſt and moſt powerfull choſen. But the ſearcher and iudge of all hearts will recompence according to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to them, as to enemies of truth. And to the ſincere louers thereof, acknowledging Gods mercies ſhewed in the adminiſtration of his owne guifts, their guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, which is the teſtimony of a good conſcience. If we looke backe, vnto the actions of certaine Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of old time euen before the age of <hi>Galen,</hi> and the admirable medicines of ſome of them: we ſhall find not impertinent to our purpoſe, that of great <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> King of Macedon. He (as <hi>Quintus Curtius</hi> in his third booke reporteth) in the extremitie of a moſt dangerous and violent diſeaſe, deſiring either preſent helpe or death, that he might hold his appointed day of battell with <hi>Darius</hi> King of Perſia; for that purpoſe, conſulted with his friends and counſellors, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy might be found in this deſperate caſe. The King diſliked al ordinary medicines, as too weake for his purpoſe. The Phyſitions would allow none ſuch as they called vnknowne. One Phyſition among the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:280:57"/> reſt, named <hi>Philip,</hi> being borne in the country Acar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nania a part of Greece, offered <hi>Alexander</hi> to make him a medicine very ſafe to be taken, which ſhould ſpeedily reſtore him to health, though the other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions knew not what it was. <hi>Parmenio</hi> a great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour and fauorite of <hi>Alexanders,</hi> diſſwaded his King from this medicine, (for he was vnwilling the King ſhould recouer as the ſequell ſhewed) and laboured to perſwade him, that this <hi>Philip</hi> the Phyſition was hired by <hi>Darius</hi> for 1000. talents to poyſon him. Yet <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> tooke that Phyſicke, and finding the effect an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his promiſe, after his health ſo ſuddenly and beyond expectation recouered, did afterwards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other accuſations, lay this for one againſt <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menio,</hi> as not wiſhing him well; which altogether made vp that Iudgment which brought him to his end. And very honorablie, both rewarded and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded <hi>Philip,</hi> to whom next vnder God, be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and acknowledged the preſeruation of his life. The working of that medicine, in the ſame place is deſcribed, not vnlike to this of mine. In this manner, <hi>Vt vero Medicamentum, &amp;c. So ſoone as the Medicine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed or ſpred it ſelfe into the veines, there might leiſurely, by little and little recouery and healthfulneſſe be perceiued in all the body. Firſt the ſpirits and heart recouered their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and after the body alſo, ſooner then could be beleeued. For Alexander after he had beene in this caſe three daies, ſhewed himſelfe to his Armie: which did not more ardently or affectionatly fixe their eyes vpon Alexander, then vpon Philip who had ſo vnexpectedly reſtored him to them: Euery one ſtriuing who ſhould firſt giue him their right hand, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and thanke him.</hi> Thus much <hi>Curtius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Semblably it is ſufficiently prooued and famouſly manifeſt, that very many great, Noble and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:280:58"/> perſonages, both men and women, ſicke either as <hi>Alexander</hi> was, or taken with other more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and violent diſeaſes, forſaken by all other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, as vncurable, haue beene by the vſe of this Medicine, through Gods grace, in very ſhort time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and reſtored to their perfect health. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto you worthy and Honourable gentlemen, who as you are the Inheritors of Nobilitie, ſo are you of gentle and noble diſpoſitions: to you I ſay, I turne my ſelfe, reſting aſſured, that you eſteeme theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating bablers, to haue ſaid nothing reall, mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, and veritable againſt me, howſoeuer they haue mooued their tongues and quills. They intend not in this caſe, your health, but my dammage: and would rather you were offered a ſilent ſacrifice in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſleepe, then ſtrike one ſaile, or vnlace one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net blowen with the winde of their malicious breath, or leeſe the price of a popular Recipe, for a Benedict Medicament, although it doe no good, ſhall doe no harme, <hi>Propter honeſtatem Medici,</hi> that is, for the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Doctor: though euery day almoſt doe giue miſerable experience, that by want of doing good, the miſchiefe increaſeth; and ſo with the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Doctor, the poore patient is lodged in his graueſend, which is harme enough, and the worſt of a maledict Medicine. Therefore as I deſire, ſo I iuſtly hope, that you will diſcerne betweene a blacke and a white: falſhood, and truth: light and darkneſſe. That you will patroniſe, defend and keepe from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, both me and the truth. If there be any doubt concerning the auouchment of the cures and good effects of this my potable gold, here ſpoken of, you haue the reports, the particular names and places, and many of their owne hand writings I keepe ready at
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:280:58"/> all times, to be ſhewed for your further content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And I am verily perſwaded, that all honeſt perſons which haue beene recouered from their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes and infirmities by the good vſe of this my pota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gold, will be ſo thankfull to God for that benefit, as to acknowledge the meanes of their recouery, and not imitate thoſe ſilent 9. Phariſes clenſed from their Leproſie by our Sauiour: which is little leſſe (if not equiualent) then againſt their owne knowledge and conſcience to deny. Of them you may know and be ſatisfied, that it hath done good to all, hurt to none: That it is a ſafe, powerfull and pleaſing Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine: euen a Prince amongſt all, analogiſing with principalitie in this. That doing much good, yet of malicious and vnſhamefull perſons it is ill ſpoken of as Princes oft times are. Let theſe worldling ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, diſprooue that I ſay, or prooue the contrary, if they can. If not, then it is time they would be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if not for conſcience ſake, yet at leaſt for ſhame (if they feare any) to be ſilent hereafter: though it were more for their honeſt account, to recant in print. Theſe great cures performed, realities, things of fact, often times, in ſundrie and diſtant places, and ſundry and diuers perſons, in ſundry and different diſeaſes, done and performed to the great good of many, and applauſed by common atteſtation, in all parts of the Realme, and many parts beyond the ſeas: This (I ſay) cannot be pocketted as not done, nor ſo eaſily vilified by a fine phraſe, a little good Latine: Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or ſence there is none in his writing, it is meere froth, and the deceitfull inſide of a rotten Egge, or worm-eaten nut: good for nothing but to befogge the cleere light of a knowne truth, and maintaine the inured practiſe of learned ſcolds. Surely, this is not,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:280:59"/> White, in any tongue, Latine or Welch, howſoeuer verſified. Theſe teſtimonies for me (which will daily increaſe) ſhall lye and remaine to all poſterities, as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Trophies, fixed in the hearts of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and honeſt men; when theſe ſtagie chartlets of theirs, ſhall not be vouchſafed an honeſt eye or eare: but caſt by for waſt paper, to ſtop muſtard pots, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther baſe offices. They are not able, to produce one Inſtance, of harme receiued by this Medicine. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as contrary, the chiefeſt, moſt polychreſticall, and greateſt magnified compoſitions (whereof (to ſpeake truth) at this day the right Ingredients bee not knowne: and againſt which ſome learned Doctors haue learnedly written) haue their Imputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the charge muſt bee either vpon the Medicine it ſelfe, or vpon the Phyſitions. Whoſe errors, if them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues will not mend, I will not excuſe. If obiection be made, that all haue not recouered, which haue taken this Medicine of mine, but ſome haue died: I confeſſe that is true. But what then? Old Age is irreuocable. Many diſeaſes alſo are either eſſentially incurable, or preuent all power of Medicines, either by the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie or malignitie <hi>Morbi acutiſſimi,</hi> or by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of timely helpe. Many alſo being eaſily to be cured at the firſt, are made deſperate and vncurable, by errors, either of Medicines directly hurtfull, or at the leaſt not helpfull, to the intollerable weakning of the poore patient, and triumph of the diſeaſe. Alſo <hi>Hippocrates</hi> telleth vs, that all diſeaſes be not curable. For the fatall and predeſtinate houre is ineuitable. There reſteth an vnknowne cauſe, which is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable counſell of God, which wil not that all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes ſhall be cured in al men. Thus much concerning the ſecond part, we will now proceede to the third.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:280:59"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PART SHEWING THE VSE OF THIS POTABLE GOLD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which <hi>Philip</hi> of Macedon, father of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ſaid of gold: That with it all Cities, Citadells, Caſtels, Forts, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes and Bulwarkes, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by nature, Art and munition thought impregnable, might be aſſaulted, laid open and conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: I may as truely, but to better vſe, affirme of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum potabile,</hi> that is, of Gold made into medicine and reduced to the forme of a potable liquor, that it doth aſſaile and oppugne all infirmities and inward diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of mans body (reſpectiuely curable, as aforeſaid.) That it alſo doth reſtore, eſtabliſh, and confirme, the vigor and ſtrength of mans body, with the naturall and vitall faculties thereof: If it be duely and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately adminiſtred, with ſuch care, caution and iudgement as becommeth the dignitie of a rationall Phyſition. For as the Captaine of an Army, hauing any peculiar exploite in hand, neglecteth no meanes, either by Military Diſcipline, or Engines of warre, to accompliſh his intended purpoſe; ſo is the Phyſition
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:280:60"/> likewiſe bound to doe. And as the clandeſtine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which lieth in Ambuſh, and appeareth not in ſight, is much more dangerous, then he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in open face; ſo likewiſe, many of our internall diſeaſes, whoſe malignitie lurkes in the inward parts, are more difficultly cured, then thoſe which maniſeſt the vttermoſt of their malice. And as in this age, both Armour and other Artillery for the ſeruice of warre, are farre different from thoſe of former times, ſo that it were ridiculous now, either in offenſiue warre or defenſiue, to relinquiſh our Ordnance of all ſorts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (in compariſon) they are but late inuentions, and to truſt to the ancient military inſtruments ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable among the Romans in thoſe daies: Euen ſo, the capitall diſeaſes of this age, being for the moſt part <hi>Complicati Morbi,</hi> whereas <hi>olim</hi> they were <hi>ſimplices,</hi> will hardly be extirpate, if we ouercuriouſly do perſiſt in the preſcript rules and method of antiquitie, and tye our ſelues only to their Medicines: ſeeing that daily experience doth teach vs, that they performe not the effects promiſed, and therefore, are for the moſt part adminiſtred fruitleſly. Seeing therefore the indeuours of this age (being inforced thereunto by defect of thoſe medicines) haue likewiſe added vnto Art, and haue inriched the ſame with other mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials medicinable, not formerly retained in common vſe; or the ſame, by more artificiall preparation, haue exalted into a higher virtue: Were it not madneſſe (the validitie of the ſame being ſufficiently experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) to relinquiſh thoſe of a higher nature, and to vſe triuiall and fruitleſſe medicines? Let the Souldier make conuenient vſe of the Sword, Dagger, Helmet, Target, Pike, and ſuch like (for they haue beene of long antiquity) but withall, let not Musket, Saker,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:280:60"/> Mineon, Cannon, be neglected, becauſe they are new inuentions, in compariſon of the other. And let vs likewiſe approue, and retaine in vſe, Electuaries, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rups, Pills, Powders, and whatſoeuer elſe by long ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation is pertinent to the expulſing of malignant humors the cauſes of maladies: yet, let not the virtues acknowledged by all antiquity to be inſident in gold, be leaſt regarded, which virtues do actually appeare in potable gold. Euery graduated Phyſition is tied by ſolemne oath, as alſo by integrity of conſcience, not to neglect any thing, tending to the recouery of his patient; But to vſe all manner of effectuall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, either new or old, whether of their owne inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or of other mens labours, being approued to be ſecure and not nauſeous: not reiecting the ſame vpon any priuate conſideration, either of preiudice or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. But leauing this digreſſion, to the intent that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery body whom it ſhall concerne, may make the beſt vſe, reape the full fruition of all benefits which they can expect by this ſo profitable and extraordinary gift of God, (although they cannot at all times haue the aſſiſtance and directing aduice of a learned Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to preſcribe and order the adminiſtration there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which were to be wiſhed) I will here in this laſt part of this Treatiſe, endeuour to helpe that defect: and teach the method, manner, and rules, how, and in what diſeaſes and paſſions, it may moſt profitable be adminiſtred. Which though by many the letters ſent me, before in this diſcourſe ſet downe as alſo by the hiſtories of many cures by my ſelfe and others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with performed, it be reaſonable plaine, yet I will draw it into a more diſtinct and orderly deliuery, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good will and meaning I haue: That by a generall helping medicine, a moſt generall and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:280:61"/> vniuerſall benefite may be reaped.</p>
            <p>Therefore be it knowne, that the vſe of this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is generally twofold, anſwerable to the two ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ends of Practicke Phyſicke. One, to preſerue the preſent health. The other, to recouer it, beeing broken or loſt: by curing the Diſeaſes, and rooting out the cauſes thereof.</p>
            <div type="account">
               <head>THE VSE OF POTABLE GOLD in preſeruation of health.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the Phyſitions and learned men, both before in my firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted booke, and here in this alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as alſo almoſt innumerable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe names I omit to auouch, for breuitie, agree in this: That <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> is the beſt Medicine, and moſt profitable Inſtrument for the conſeruation of health, in all kinde of complexiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble temperaments; That it partly ſuppreſſeth and ſuffereth not luxuriouſly to bud, ſhoot out, and bring their fruit vnto ripeneſſe, any ſeedes, or latent rootes of ſickneſſes, lurking in mans body, whereunto any proneneſſe or aptitude hereditarie, or otherwiſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall, make them obnoxious: That it reduceth to mediocritie, inordinate diſtemperatures, either in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe or defect: That it refreſheth, vigorateth, and ſtrengthneth the heart; reſtoreth, and increaſeth the vitall ſpirits: aduanceth the force and and generation
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:280:61"/> of good blood, multiplieth geniture ſeede, and habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of prolification in both ſexes; baniſhing ſterility, preuenting abortions, and prouiding quicke, eaſy, and ſafe deliueries in childbed, ſuppreſſeth the infirmities of age: preſerueth the vigor of youth. It were vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to heape arguments in confirmation hereof, being in it ſelfe ſo authentically warranted by famous authors, and manifeſtly witneſſed by many experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Particularly, it is a preſeruatiue againſt the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſickneſſe,, the Apoplexie, Leproſie, Plague, Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, Cancer, Gout, Stone, and all manner of feuers in all ages and ſexes. And in ſome, it expelleth (or rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableth the body to expell) by conuenient and moſt naturall paſſages, the antecedent matter or humors, from and by which any diſeaſes depending vpon ſuch materiall cauſes might ſpring, and ſo by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, preſerueth health.</p>
               <p>But it is to be knowne and obſerued, that this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine<note place="margin">The firſt forme.</note> of gold, though made of one body, yet is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vſed in three formes and conſiſtences; which not being knowne, there may be much miſtaking and errour in the vſe and adminiſtration thereof.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when the gold is diſſolued in the proper menſtruall or inſtrumentall water, this water is diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away from the diſſolued gold, vntill it be in the bottome in the forme or conſiſtence of a liquid gum or hony, deepely coloured (as <hi>Raymund Lully</hi> cals it) &amp; moſt vnctuous. To which, the ſpirit of wine is then put, and by ſolution thereof, tincted very red and deepe coloured. That tincted ſpirit of wine is gently decanted, or powred off, and ſo reſerued by it ſelfe in a glaſſe. And is called the Phyſicall Tincture of gold. And may ſo, in ſmall roome, and with no burden bee caried whither any man pleaſe. And this we call the firſt forme.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:280:62"/>
               <p>Take one ounce of this tincted ſpirit, mixe it with<note place="margin">The ſecond forme.</note> 16. ounces of generous wine (or if you pleaſe, of any other liquor.) And this being ſo mixed is called that Potable golde, of which ſo often mention hath beene hitherto made. One, or two ſpoonfuls of this at one time, and ſometimes a whole ounce, I accuſtome to giue, in ſuch caſes and Diſeaſes as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The third forme is this, and thus made. That tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted<note place="margin">The third forme.</note> red ſpirit of wine, in which the diſſolued gold is taken vp from the white feces, or reſidence, is put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fit glaſſe body with a head. And with a gentle heate of a <hi>Balneum,</hi> the ſpirit is drawne off, vntill the ſubſtance in the bottome of the glaſſe be dry. Then doe I put on freſh ſpirit of wine, ſetting it in digeſtion certaine daies. In which time it will caſt off an other reſidence. This proceſſe is reiterated, and at euery ſuch ſolution and diſtillation, the feculent reſidence muſt be ſeparated from the pure, vntill it leaue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence at all. Then is it called the Quinteſſence or Eſſence of God, which I doe vſe to adminiſter in the quantity of 2. or 3. or more graines, and doe diſſolue it in ſome appropriate liquor or other mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conducent.</p>
               <p>So that any, that is deſirous to make vſe of this my Medicine, may haue either the Potable gold, or the Tincture of gold, or the Eſſence of gold, or all; and apply them in all manner of needfull vſes, as occaſion ſhall require.</p>
               <p>They therefore that ſhall take it for preſeruation, may vſe it in the ſimpleſt &amp; leaſt curious order &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. That is, to take of the <hi>Auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Potabile</hi> one or two ſpoonfuls, together faſting, and in bed, if they may, elſe in the morning after they be vp; the oftner, the better. Vſe giues inſtruction, from that common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication aforeſaid, <hi>A Iuuantibus et nocentibus, &amp;c,</hi> From
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:280:62"/> things that helpe and hurt, euery one is directed. Therefore whoſoeuer after twice or thrice taking, hath found benefit thereby, he may proportion him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in moderate increaſing or diminiſhing the doſe or quantitie, according to his owne hability and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. For, in increaſing the quantitie of this, there is no danger, ſo it be within any bounds of mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, not exorbitantly <hi>exuberatè:</hi> which is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in all or moſt part of other ſimples and compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whether meerely Medicaments, or Midica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall nutriments, as are Oximel, Saffron, Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date, Treacle, all Cordiales and Purges whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Alſo a conuenient time to take it (eſpecially in thoſe that haue weake ſtomacks) will be one houre or two before dinner or ſupper, or after ſupper, at bed time (for it doth both helpe digeſtion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſleepe) according as the circumſtances ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire or ſuffer.</p>
               <p>In precaution of Lunarie Diſeaſes, ſuch as haue their exacerbations &amp; fits according to the quarters, changings, &amp; full of the Moone, as <hi>Epilepſies, Defluxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> inordinate <hi>Menſtruals</hi> and ſuch like: The rule is, for this laſt, to take it neere the time of courſe: In the other, 3. 4. or 5. daies before the new and full Moone.</p>
               <p>If it be deſired for the more particular appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this Medicine to any particular cauſe, to take it not ſo ſimply of it ſelfe, but mixed: Then let ſuch, either by their owne knowledge, or the appointment of ſome experienced Phyſition, mixe it with ſome ſpecificall water, decoction, extraction, or otherwiſe formed Medicine, according to the neceſſitie of euery particular cauſe and occaſion: Or with ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound water, approoued for that Diſeaſe, or Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chreſtall to the ſame, and others, in neighbourhood and linke of cauſes to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:280:63"/>
               <head>THE VSE OF AVRVM POTABILE IN SVNDRY INFIRMITIES.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſeaſed perſon that ſhall vſe this Medicine, may take it in the ſame proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or doſe, as formerly is ſet downe, or ſomewhat greater or leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the condition of the partie, and ſtate of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. Commonly one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> is giuen at one time: or ſixe<note place="margin">The doſe.</note> or eight droppes of the Tincture of gold, mixed in ſome appropriate liquor: and of the Eſſence of Gold, two or three graines. Where neceſſitie ſhall require, theſe doſes may be doubled, or more; as of the <hi>Aurum Potabile,</hi> two or three ſpoonfull vnto a full ounce: of the Eſſence foure graines or ſixe: Of the Tincture in like reſpect. Alſo in ſome perſons greatly debilitated, and not able well to retaine, a ſmall quantity is firſt to be attempted, and then by degrees increaſed, as by former examples may plainly appeare. Alſo this Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of gold is very fitting and conuenient for very yong infants but newly borne, in any Diſeaſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, being ordered in this maner. Take one graine of the Eſſence, diſſolue it in one or two ſpoonfull of breſtmilke or in ſome diſtilled water as ſhal be fitting:
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:280:63"/> giue the childe part of that mixture at the firſt: after a while giue it more. This is ſecurely giuen, the third or fourth day after the birth; ſo is likewiſe the <hi>Aurum Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabile</hi> in a ſmall quantitie, and mixed with ſome other liquor, not with milke: neither muſt the childe ſucke within two houres after, leſt the wine in the potable gold, ſhould curdle the milke.</p>
               <p>Theſe adminiſtrations are to be giuen intermiſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">How oft.</note> ſometime euery ſecond, third, or fourth houre, as the preſent caſe ſhall require: vntill of the operation appeare with good ſignes, the abating of the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diminiſhing of the Diſeaſe, and recouerie of ſtrength.</p>
               <p>It may be giuen at al times, moſt commonly in the<note place="margin">When to be giuen.</note> morning faſting, or an houre before repaſt. Likewiſe after meate to preuent a ſurfet. For it helpeth digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and preuenteth ſickneſſes following ſuch repleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To procure ſleepe it is giuen at bed-time; or if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie vrge, in any other houre of the night or day: being effectually a true Anodine, of contemperation without ſtupefaction, not narcoticke.</p>
               <p>The Effects of this Medicine: corroboration of<note place="margin">Effects.</note> the heart: reſtauration of the vitall ſpirits decaied and enfeebled: which apparantly is manfeſt, by quiet and ſweete ſleepe moſt commonly following; as alſo by mitigation of paine, and appeaſing of violent paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſometime by a milde and gentle ſweat enſuing, ſometimes by vomit, and reiection of malignant viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous humors: alſo by plentifull euacation of vrine, as alſo by reſtraint thereof, where the retention is weake. And though ſildom, yet ſomtimes by a looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the belly: but very oft, by ſtaying inordinate fluxes. And euery of theſe functions, though contrary ſome one to other, are directed and performed by the meere motion of Nature it ſelfe, being ſtrengthned,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:280:64"/> vigorated, and enabled, by the virtue of this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
               <p>Let thus much ſuffice, for the ſimple, or very ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply mixed vſe of this Medicine. But although in this forme taken and vſed, it giueth great furtherance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the curing of any malady, as by many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar experiments hath beene related, in which ſildome times any addition of peculiar effect hath beene ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred: yet becauſe of the great varietie, difference and diuerſitie of diſpoſitions, natures, places, diſeaſes, times, and countries; and becauſe preſcription ought not to preiudicate the skill and iudgement of all men; Therefore to ſupply theſe differences, I doe leaue free to the iudgement and diſcretion of euery rationall experienced Phyſition, to adminiſter this medicine, with any kind of Waters, Liquors, Syrups, Conſerues, Electuaries, or other medicines ſimple or compound, ſuch as they ſhall vpon good grounds and experience, know or iudge moſt appropriate, ſpecificall, conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and agreeing to the preſent circumſtances of the diſeaſe, nature, &amp; quality of the patient, &amp; neceſſity of his ſtate. We giue no preſcript of Method, or limitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of proceedings vnto Phyſitions; they being preſent, know what is needfull, what requiſite, in order, time and place: what in each reſpect is to be done, what to be left vndone. But where a competent Phyſition is not at hand, as in Country villages, or ſuch like pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there ſome admonition or direction is expedient.</p>
               <p>It is well knowne among learned men, what effect, efficacy, and force, is attributed to that Medicine which is called Vniuerſall, in that high degree where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of writers make mention, that it performeth great and admirable effect, not only vpon mans body, but alſo vpon Mettals, as appeareth by theſe words of <hi>Raymund Lully: The quinteſſence of gold, after diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:280:64"/> away of the inſtrumentall water, will remaine in the bottome of the glaſſe, very pure, and ſeparated from all impurity, thicke in the conſiſtence of hony, or of gumme, deepely coloured and very vnctuous, greatly auaileable, both for Medicine of many body, as alſo of Mettals. But this Medicine of ours, hath his preparation onely pertinent to the vſe of man. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles ſeeing that, both that Medicine of <hi>Raymund Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and this of mine, haue all the virtue incident vnto them deriued from gold, and from the forme thereof, as from one fountaine and foundation; therefore it will not be impertinent, to preſcribe the ſame vſe and manner of adminiſtring of this medicine of mine, which <hi>Raymund</hi> doth vnto his. For if the agent cauſe be one in them both, the manner of vſe may alſo be the ſame. He preſcribeth a ſpeciall vſe in theſe words. Mixe this Eſſence of gold in a quantity of white wine, when you will giue it to a Phlegmaticke conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eſpecially in the Winter ſeaſon. If to a Cholericke, giue it in faire water: to a Melancholike, in broth, wherein mutton is decocted: If he be of a Sanguine complexion, in cleare white wine: And this ſhall be a preuention againſt infirmities, and their bodies ſhall be rectified againſt the diſtemper of the ſeaſon. If you giue this medicine to thoſe that are ſicke, let the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be more effectuall of the Medicine. Neither be thou greatly troubled (ſaith he) to know the perfect ſtate of the diſeaſe. For nature it ſelfe is wiſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident by her owne inſtinct, and hath inueſted to this ſtone being diſſolued, ſufficient virtues, to rectifie that which is amiſſe in nature. <hi>My ſonne, this medicine is powerfull, both againſt hotte diſeaſes, and cold, naturall, and accidentiall,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe words and other here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto tending <hi>Raymund</hi> ſetteth downe, which we out of our experience haue found to be anſwerable to this
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:280:65"/> our intent. Neuertheleſſe wee acknowledge, that ſometimes extraordinary ſymptomes doe occurre, which threaten preſent danger of death, if they bee not ſpeedily preuented: As is, extreme heate, extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of cold, great thirſt, lacke of ſleepe, inordinate fluxes, and ſuch like. All which by the good pleaſure of God, are mitigated and aſſwaged by this only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of mine. And yet many things may be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priately added hereunto, &amp; pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the expulſing of euery Diſeaſe. Therfore, if the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t haue a repleate body, that neceſſity require ſome euacuation to bee made; gentle, &amp; not viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t purges, fitting the humor offending, are to be adminiſtred. Sometime the body hath neede by vrine or ſweat to be releeued: which both, although this <hi>Aurum Potabile</hi> doe in ſort per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme yet in ſome caſes it is to be helped. If a fluxe be cauſed in the nether ventricle, vnto which a Medicine receiued at the mouth cannot ſpeedily penetrate, then a clenſing, and aſtringent Gliſter will be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. If ſleepe be wanting, that neceſſarily muſt be regarded. And although this Medicine doth for the moſt part by a ſecret proprietie therin procure ſleepe, yet if neede be, let other helps be adioyned. Blood letting in conuenient time muſt not be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. Other things pertinent, I referre to the diſcretion of them, whome it ſhall concerne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:280:65"/>
            <head>THE CONCLVSION OF THIS TREATISE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing thus, ingenuouſly, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and fully (as I hope) ſatisfied all indifferent and vnpartiable Readers, of the cauſe of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, concerning the generall and extraordinarie effects of this Medicine: and of the three kinds thereof: of my vſe in adminiſtration thereof, in all Diſeaſes, ſexes, ages and circumſtances: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the libertie and cautions in further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and mixture with other Medicines: I now returne in the Concluſion, vnto ſuch Readers, to whome I haue and euer ſhall, deuote, conſecrate and dedicate all my ſtudies, labours and induſtrie, commending vnto you the right conſtruction, and generous acceptance, without any ſiniſter detortion, of my good and vnſpotted intendements, not retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt my traducers, with any malicious viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but extorted by meere compulſion, for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary challenge, and defence of my good name, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned by two Doctors, though neuer expugnable by them, nor the laudatorie verſifiers, chaunting <hi>pro formâ abſque materiâ.</hi> Let them enioy the glory of their Eloquence, or rather loquence, with ill applyed Phraſes. I deſire none other contentment in this
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:280:66"/> queſtion, then the publike teſtimony of a conſtant truth. Truth will ſurely liue, preuaile, flouriſh. It is like the gentle and ſweete Marierome, manifoldly excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for many vertues. Which but rubbed in the hand, yeeldeth an excellent ſent, comfortable to all ſenſes. Of which hearb it is written, that if ſwine be enforced, with full ſent of open noſtrels to take the ſmell, it is mortall to them, and cauſeth them to die. Surely this is a ſecret in Nature, that a thing ſo good in it ſelfe, and ſo agreeably helpefull to good men, ſhould by the malice, or brutiſhneſſe of a Swiniſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be accounted poyſon. This is a true Embleme of my Medicine, which being helpfull to all, hurtfull to none, yet there are found ſuch, as profeſſe hatred to the very name thereof: and ſo turne that generall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue, to their priuate poyſon of rancor. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that common rule of Philoſophy, is not vnfitly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogiſed vpon them: <hi>Nutriens conuertitur in naturam nutriti, et non contra.</hi> The nouriſhment is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted into the nature of the body nouriſhed, but not contrarily. So likewiſe the enuious man, whatſoeuer hee behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with his malicious Eye, though extraordinary good of it ſelfe, yet hee conuerteth it to his owne peruerſe diſpoſition, which is euill. As may well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Bee, and the Spyder, this ſucking poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the other hony out of the ſelfe ſame flower. Let all theſe things be conſidered, by the indifferent and Iudicious Reader, and with equall ballance let him peiſe truth with falſehood, ſinceritie with deceit, not inclining either to hatred or adulation, but with free minde and integritie of conſcience, let ſentence be pronounced. Among good men there ought to be good dealing. It may peraduenture bee that ſome doubts may bee mooued, or cauilling allegations
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:280:66"/> againſt the tract of this Treatiſe in ſome point or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but ſurely ſuch as will be vtterly vnprofitable to the ſicke patient, who is to be releeued by healthfull Medicine, and not by ſubtilitie of Argument. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if I ſhould endeauour to anſwer euery friuolous and idle obiection, I ſhould both abuſe the Reader, and thinke mine owne time euill ſpent. Some few things I deſire to admoniſh the Reader: Firſt, fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie to conſtrue and interpet the intent of theſe my proceedings, &amp; not raſhly, vpon any mans words or writings, to condemne the verity of this matter now in queſtion. Alſo, if any thing in this Treatiſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which ſeemeth not anſwerable vnto euery mans capacitie or iudgement, that ſuch perſon would be pleaſed, firſt, to admoniſh mee thereof by priuate letters, or otherwiſe, that I may in thoſe doubts yeeld him ſatisfaction, before hee doe publikely oppugne the truth. Furthermore, if theſe things to ſome, ſeeme of ſmall moment, I humbly intreate them, to produce better in place for the vſe of the languiſhing patient (prouided alwaies that it bee no leſſe approued by time and experience) and in the mean time, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt wee liue in expectation thereof, let the Common-wealth receiue benefit by this, without their let or preiudice.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:280:67"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX <hi>RESERVED FOR</hi> THE IVDICIOVS READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is generally well knowne, that <hi>Mathew Gwinne,</hi> in the Preface of that his Invectiue booke againſt me, did, in moſt inſtant manner, ſollicite the Kings Maieſtie, for the ſuppreſſion of this Medicine my Potable gold. His Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and motiues were in theſe words. <hi>Tolluntur vnà Medici, &amp;c. The Phyſitions of this Citie, the Chyrurgians, and the Apothecaries will all decay, and in manner be ſubuerted; if this one vniuerſall Medicine of Anthony doe preuaile.</hi> He enforceth the ſame as yet further: <hi>Let your Maieſtie eſtabliſh this, leaſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chytectonicall order of the Phyſitions,</hi> (for I doe produce his owne words) <hi>the Polychreſt all order of the Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: the honeſt, learned, &amp; wealthy order of the London Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, be either confuſed, or vtterly confounded, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion of thoſe who prepare Medicines Chymically.</hi> How vniuſt this petition is, and how preiudiciall vnto ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie it ſelfe, and vnto true Art (whereof the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries haue but a ſhaddow) who ſeeth not? If God
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:280:67"/> hath granted vnto this our age, an extraordinary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, more ſeruiceable for the health of man, and much more auaileable then all other Medicaments hitherto retained in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vſe, ought it to be explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the practitioners in Phyſicke, or to be reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of the patient in his vtter diſtreſſe, becauſe the like lucre and gaine doth not to them aforeſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound, as by other drugges ordinarily preſcribed? Was that elect Veſſel (mentioned in holy writ) iuſtly ſcourged and vtterly ſilenced, becauſe by his words and admonition, the handicraftſmen, employed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that idoll of <hi>Diana,</hi> were likely to loſe ſome part of their vſuall lucre and gaine? (I hope it is not vnlawfull in this caſe, to compare profane with ſacred actions.) Nay rather contrariwiſe. If this vniuerſall Medicine, ſhall approoue it ſelfe by daily experience to be vniuerſally effectuall, then being retained in vſe, both Phyſitions, Chyrurgions, and Apothecaries, will the rather be accepted of, and the more reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: Neither will that three-fold order, bee either confuſed, or confounded herewith but rather confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and better ſetled in generall account. For if theſe three, when they ſhall be called to the ſicke pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, would at their entrance (as the ancient Ethnick Senators vſed to doe, when they entred the Senate houſe for conſultations of the Weale publike) ſhake off aemulation, Enuy, and ouermuch deſire of filthy lucre: then the Phyſition ſhould finde in this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, ſuch helpe in deſperate Diſeaſes, as both he and his languiſhing patient ſhould reioyce at the fruites thereof. The Chyrurgians likewiſe, in ſome caſe of theirs, as in Faintings, Swoundings, Convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Crampes, and where ſleepe and reſt are wanting, whereby great feebleneſſe and deiection of Spirits
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:280:68"/> doe enſue ſhould then make perfect experience and tryall, of what validitie this Medicine is. Then alſo the Apothecarie ſhould loſe no part of his honeſtie, of his learning, nor of his ſubſtance and riches, hauing by him this Medicine, as a laſt refuge for the releefe of his forlorne patient. The Apothecarie is carefull, to haue in euery corner of his ſhoppe, diuers and ſundrie contemptible drugges, loathſome to moſt men, now in this age of ours. My deſire is not to detract any thing from them in their gaine or skill, but rather to adde thereunto, and the behalfe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, vnto whom I doe here dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, conſecrate and offer, all theſe my labours; and whatſoeuer elſe is in my power.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:280:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
